<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Catechistical guide to sinners, and to such converts that are babes in Christ wherein all the necessary points of religion are methodically proposed in Scripture-language, abundantly confirmed by the Holy Scriptures, and in some places concisely expounded : in the whole, all controversies are warily shunn'd, so that all true Christians, of what persuassion soever, may (if they need the help of others) use this catechism for their children, or others that are under their power and card / written upon request, by a lover of truth and peace.</title>
            <author>Norton, John, 1606-1663.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1680</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 170 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 74 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A31334</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C1480</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R9600</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12384596</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12384596</idno>
            <idno type="VID">60817</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A31334)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 60817)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 933:25)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Catechistical guide to sinners, and to such converts that are babes in Christ wherein all the necessary points of religion are methodically proposed in Scripture-language, abundantly confirmed by the Holy Scriptures, and in some places concisely expounded : in the whole, all controversies are warily shunn'd, so that all true Christians, of what persuassion soever, may (if they need the help of others) use this catechism for their children, or others that are under their power and card / written upon request, by a lover of truth and peace.</title>
                  <author>Norton, John, 1606-1663.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 140 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.D., to be sold by Fr. Smith ... and W. Crook ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1680.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catechisms --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:60817:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:60817:1"/>
            <p>Catechiſtical Guide TO SINNERS, And to ſuch CONVERTS that are Babes in Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Wherein all the neceſſary Points of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion are methodically propoſed in Scripture-Language, abundantly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by the Holy Scriptures, and in ſome Places conciſely expounded.</p>
            <p>In the whole, all Controverſies are warily ſhunn'd: So that all true Chriſtians, of what Perſuaſion ſoever, may (if they need the help of others) uſe this Catechiſm for their Children, or others that are under their Power and Care.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Written upon requeſt, by a lover of Truth and Peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. D.</hi> to be ſold by <hi>Fr. Smith</hi> at the Elephant and Caſtle in <hi>Cornhil,</hi> and <hi>W. Crook</hi> at the Green-Dragon without <hi>Temple-Bar:</hi> 1680.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:60817:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:60817:2"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>READER,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THe Author of this Catechiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Diſcourſe was well aware, that the World abounds with Catechiſms, and himſelf had read and conſider'd very many of them, written not only in our Engliſh; but in the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin and Greek Tongues, and yet he was perſwaded there was ſomewhat wanting, which he has, with great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry and accuracy, endeavour'd to ſupply. And I am perſwaded, whoever he be that reads this with conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, will find it well worth his labour: for thô he may thereby add nothing to his Knowledg, yet he may be well pleas'd to ſee the neceſſary things of Chriſtian Religion deliver'd in ſo plain a Method, ſo diſtinctly, and with ſuch pertinency of Scripture-Proofs. In all which, and eſpecially in
<pb facs="tcp:60817:3"/>the laſt, it is too uſual to be defective. Yea, even Scripture-Catechiſms, wherein the Anſwers to the Queſtions are made wholly in Scripture Sentences, are too often found faulty in that kind. He has (as he tells you in his Title Page) warily ſhunn'd all controverted Points, that ſo he might ſhew that one may be a true Chriſtian without determining them, and that Children, and weak Perſons of all Parties, may be inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in all things neceſſary to Salvation without medling with them; that ſo (as the Apoſtle ſays) <hi>He that is weak may be receiv'd, but not to doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Diſputations.</hi> Surely if this were diligently perform'd, it would tend much to the promoting of Peace and Love among Chriſtians.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="part">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:60817:3"/>
            <head>A Catechiſtical Guide, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <head>The Firſt Part.</head>
            <head type="sub">Setting forth the <hi>Chriſtian Religion</hi> in general.</head>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>WHat is the best and chiefeſt thing we are to learn?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The beſt and chiefeſt thing we are to learn, is, That Doctrine which teacheth us to know God, and Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>What do you mean by this name, God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> By this name [God] I mean,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:60817:4"/>Him, who is the moſt High, and chiefeſt Lord, Ruler, and Governour of all things.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>What mean you by theſe names, Jeſus Chriſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> By theſe names, Jeſus Chriſt, I mean, The only Son of God, who was conceived by the Holy Ghoſt, and born of a Virgin.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>Where may we find this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine that teacheth us to know God, and Jeſus Christ?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> This Doctrine that teacheth us to know God, and Jeſus Chriſt, we may find in the Holy Scriptures of the Old Teſtament and the New; but eſpecially in the Holy Scriptures of the New Teſtament, or Covenant.</p>
            <p>[Jeſus Chriſt ſaid to the Jews; <hi>Search the Scriptures, for in them ye think ye have eternal Life, and they are they which teſtify of me,</hi> John 5.39. <hi>Luke</hi> teſtifieth of thoſe of <hi>Berea</hi> thus; <hi>Theſe were more noble than thoſe of</hi> Theſſalonica; <hi>in that they received the Word with all readineſs of mind, and ſearched the Scriptures daily, whether theſe things were ſo,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Act.</hi> 17.11. The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:60817:4"/>ſaith thus to <hi>Timothy; Continue thou in the things which thou haſt learned, and haſt been aſſured of, knowing of whom thou haſt learned them: and that from a Child thou haſt known the Holy Scriptures, which are able to make thee wiſe unto Salvation, through Faith which is in Chriſt Jeſus. All Scripture is given by inſpiration of God, and is profitable for Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, for Reproof, for Correction, for Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in Righteouſneſs; that the Man of God may be perfect, thorowly furniſhed unto all good works,</hi> 2 Tim. 3.14, 15, 16, 17. Thus St. <hi>Luke</hi> begins his Hiſtory of Jeſus Chriſt: <hi>Foraſmuch as many have taken in hand to ſet forth in order a Declaration of thoſe things which are moſt ſurely believed among us, even as they delivered them unto us, which from the beginning were Eye-witneſſes and Miniſters of the Word: It ſeemed good to me alſo, having had perfect underſtanding of all things from the very firſt, to write unto thee in order, moſt excellent</hi> Theophilus, <hi>that thou mighteſt know the certainty of thoſe things wherein thou haſt been inſtructed,</hi> Luke 1.1, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Thus the Apoſtle <hi>John</hi> ſaith of his Goſpel: <hi>Theſe things are written, that ye might believe that Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus is the Chriſt, the Son of God, and that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving ye might have life through his Name,</hi> John 20.21. The ſame <hi>John</hi> in his firſt Epiſtle hath this ſaying: <hi>That which we have
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:60817:5"/>ſeen and heard, declare we unto you, that ye alſo may have fellowſhip with us; and truly our fellowſhip is with the Father, and with his Son Jeſus Chriſt. And theſe things write we unto you that your joy may be full,</hi> 1 Joh. 1.3, 4. <hi>ſee</hi> Chap. 5.13. Epheſ. 3.3, 4. 1 Tim. 3.14, 15. 1 Pet. 5.12. 2 Pet. 1.12, 13.]</p>
            <p>* Queſt. <hi>But why do you ſay that this Doctrine is to be found, eſpecially in the Holy Scriptures of the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>* <hi>Anſw.</hi> It may be ſaid, That the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine which teacheth us to know God, and Jeſus Chriſt, is to be found eſpecially in the Scriptures of the New Teſtament, for theſe cauſes.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe that of this Doctrine which was hidden in the Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and there contained in a My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery, is in the New Teſtament open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and revealed.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Becauſe the New Teſtament is an Hiſtory of many things, which we are to believe as already done; which in the Old Teſtament are only pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſied of, and promiſed.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:60817:5"/>
            <p n="3">3. Becauſe there are ſome things added in the New Teſtament, which are not to be found in the Old.</p>
            <p>[Rom. 16. v. 25, 26, 27. <hi>Now to him that is of power to eſtabliſh you according to my Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, and the preaching of Jeſus Chriſt (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the revelation of the Myſtery, which was kept ſecret ſince the World began; but now is made manifeſt, and by the Scriptures of the Prophets, according to the Commandment of the everlaſting God, made known to all Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for the obedience of Faith) to God only wiſe be glory through Jeſus Chriſt for ever.</hi> Amen. Luke 24 24, <hi>&amp;c. And Jeſus ſaid unto them, Theſe are the words which I ſpake unto you, while I was yet with you, that all things muſt be fulfilled which are written in the Law of</hi> Moſes, <hi>and in the Prophets, and in the</hi> Pſalms <hi>concerning me. Then opened he their underſtandings, that they might underſtand the Scriptures; And ſaid unto them, Thus it is written, and thus it behoved Chriſt to ſuffer, and to riſe from the Dead the third day,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>See</hi> Acts 13.36, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 1 Pet. 1.10, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 1 Cor. 11.2, 3.]</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>Can you ſhew me from the Scripture, that the Doctrine there decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, teacheth us to know God, and Jeſus Chriſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:60817:6"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Yes; for Jeſus Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in his Prayer to the Father, ſaid; <hi>This is Life Eternal,</hi> [that is, This is that which the Doctrine, that hath the promiſe of Eternal Life, does teach and require for the obtaining of Eternal Life, to wit] <hi>that they may know thee the only truly God, and Jeſus Chriſt whom thou hast ſent,</hi> Joh. 17.3.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>Well: But what does Jeſus Christ here intend by Mens knowing him who is the only true God, and Jeſus Chriſt whom he hath ſent?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> To know him who is the only true God, and Jeſus Chriſt whom he hath ſent, is (according to Chriſt's intendment here) not only to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand or apprehend, that which muſt be known concerning him, who is the only true God, and Jeſus Chriſt whom he hath ſent; but alſo, to love them as ſuch, or according to ſuch a know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of them to acknowledg them.</p>
            <p>* Queſt. <hi>But how can you prove that Jeſus Christ here intendeth ſuch a know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg as this?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:60817:6"/>
            <p>* <hi>Anſw.</hi> That Jeſus Chriſt here in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendeth ſuch a knowledg of things neceſſary to be known concerning the only true God, and him whom he hath ſent, which has a ſuitable love to them, or anſwerable acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of them joined therewith, I am able clearly to prove, and that abundantly.</p>
            <p>* Queſt. The proof of this being very needful, I am willing to hear it, and therefore I now ask you, <hi>How it may be confirmed?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Firſt, I ſhall offer this; That theſe Phraſes or Expreſſions, <hi>To know God,</hi> and <hi>To know Jeſus Christ,</hi> are oftentimes ſo uſed in the Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures: Whence I gather, that it is not ſtrange ſo to accept and take them here; <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 53.4. <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.16. <hi>Jer.</hi> 9.3. Ch. 31.34. <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.11. <hi>Dan.</hi> 11.32. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 2.20. <hi>Joh.</hi> 15.21. Ch. 17.25. 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4.5. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 36.10. <hi>Job</hi> 18.21. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53.11. 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.3, 4. Ch. 4.6.</p>
            <p>* Queſt. You do well to infer no more, ſeeing theſe Phraſes are fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:60817:7"/>reſtrained to a meer know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg or notion of God and Chriſt; or for knowledg as diſtinct from Love and Acknowledgment: Yea, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times they are ſaid to know God, and to know Chriſt, who have only the means of knowing them, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.21. <hi>Joh.</hi> 8.28. <hi>But what ground have you to conclude, that in this ſaying of Chriſt, Love and Acknowledgment is implied in know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>* <hi>Anſw.</hi> It plainly appears that Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt here intends ſuch a know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg as implies in it Love and Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgment, if we conſider only this, That Chriſt here declares this to be ſufficient for obtaining Eternal Life; namely, To know the Father the only true God, and Jeſus Chriſt whom he hath ſent. Now it is in it ſelf abſurd to conceive, that it is enough only to underſtand and noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Truth concerning God and Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>* Queſt. It is ſo: <hi>But have you any thing more to ſay in confirming it?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:60817:7"/>
            <p>* <hi>Anſw.</hi> I ſhall add this; That the Scriptures declare expreſly, that more than meerly to know, or only to underſtand God and Jeſus Chriſt, is neceſſary for obtaining Eternal Life. This is ſo well known, that the citing of places will be needleſs; notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding I will repeat the ſaying of the Apoſtle <hi>Paul, Knowledg puffeth up, but Charity</hi> [Love] <hi>edifieth,</hi> 1 Cor. 8.1. The Devils have knowledg of God and Chriſt, <hi>Jam.</hi> 2.19. <hi>Mar.</hi> 1.24. <hi>Act.</hi> 19.15. And ſo have ſome of the worſt of Men.</p>
            <p>Queſt. Seeing it is ſo as you have ſaid, we may draw up, concerning the Doctrine we are chiefly to learn, theſe two Propoſitions:</p>
            <p n="1">1. That it teacheth us to know or apprehend him who is the only true God, and Jeſus Chriſt whom he hath ſent.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That it teacheth to love or ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg him who is the only true God, and Jeſus Chriſt whom he hath ſent.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:60817:8"/>
            <p>Concerning theſe two, I deſire now to hear from you a general and brief Account what you have learned out of the Holy Scriptures. And firſt I will ask you ſome Queſtions touching the firſt Propoſition. And my firſt Query ſhall be this:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>What are we to underſtand by the only true God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> By the only true God we are to underſtand, the only Creator and moſt high Lord, or Governor of all things.</p>
            <p>[2 Kings 19.19. <hi>Now therefore, O Lord our God, I beſeech thee, ſave us out of his hand, that all the Kingdoms of the Earth may know that thou art the Lord God, even thou only.</hi> Jude 4. <hi>Certain Men crept in—denying the only Lord God, and our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> 2 King. 19.15. <hi>And</hi> Hezekiah <hi>prayed before the Lord, and ſaid, O Lord God of</hi> Iſrael <hi>which dwelleſt between the Cherubims, thou art the God, even thou alone, of all the Kingdoms of the Earth; thou haſt made Heaven and Earth.</hi> Iſa. 44.24, &amp;c. <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord thy Redeemer, and he that formed thee from the Womb, I am the Lord that maketh all things, that ſtretcheth forth the Heavens alone,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:60817:8"/>that ſpreadeth abroad the Earth by my ſelf; that fruſtrateth the Tokens of the Lyars,</hi> &amp;c. Nehem. 9.6, &amp;c. <hi>Thou, even thou art Lord alone, thou haſt made Heaven, the Heaven of Heavens with all their Hoſt, the Earth and all things that are therein, the Seas and all that is therein; and thou preſerveſt them all, and the Hoſt of Heaven worſhippeth thee,</hi> &amp;c. Dan. 5.18, &amp;c. <hi>O thou King, the moſt high God gave</hi> Nebuchadnezzar <hi>thy Father a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>But when his heart was lifted up, and his mind hardned in pride, he was depoſed from his Kingly Throne,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>till he knew that the moſt high God ruled in the Kingdom of Men, and that he appointeth over it whomſoever he will.</hi> Rom. 1.25. <hi>They ſerved the Creature more than the Creator, who is bleſſed for ever.</hi> Amen. Matth. 11.25. <hi>At that time Jeſus anſwered and ſaid, I thank thee, O Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Lord of Heaven and Earth,</hi> &amp;c. Pſal. 22.18. <hi>The Kingdom is the Lords, and he is the Governour among the Nations.</hi> Rom. 11.36. <hi>Of him, and through him, and to him are all things: to whom be glory for ever.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>What are we to underſtand by Him whom the Father hath ſent?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> By him whom the Father hath ſent, we are to underſtand him whom the Father hath ſent to be
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:60817:9"/>the Saviour of the World.</p>
            <p>[1 John 4.14. <hi>And we have ſeen, and do teſtify, That the Father ſent the Son to be the Saviour of the World.</hi> John 6.39, 40. <hi>And this is the Father's Will, which hath ſent me, that of all which he hath given me, I ſhould loſe nothing, but ſhould raiſe it up again at the laſt day,</hi> &amp;c.]</p>
            <p>Queſt. Now concerning the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Propoſition, I ſhall ask you ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Queſtions; as firſt, <hi>How can you prove from the Scriptures, that we must not only know him who is the only true God, but alſo love him as ſuch?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> We are not only to know him who is the only true God, but alſo to love him as ſuch: For it is written, <hi>Hear, O</hi> Iſrael, <hi>The Lord our God is one Lord. And thou ſhalt love the Lord thy God with all thine Heart, and with all thy Soul, and with all thy Might;</hi> Deut. 6.4, 5. Mat. 12.29, 30.</p>
            <p>[<hi>Knowledg puffeth up, but Love edifieth: And if any Man think that he knoweth any thing, he knoweth nothing yet as he ought to know. But if any Man love God, the ſame is known of him;</hi> 1 Cor. 8.1, 2, 3. <hi>ſee</hi> 1 John 4.7, 8.]</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:60817:9"/>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>How does our love to God manifest and diſcover it ſelf?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Our Love to God diſcovers it ſelf, by our keeping the Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God, which require us to truſt in him, and live to him, as the only true God.</p>
            <p>[Deut. 10.12. <hi>And now</hi> Iſrael, <hi>what doth the Lord thy God require of thee, but to fear the Lord thy God, to walk in all his ways, and to love him; and to ſerve the Lord thy God with all thy Heart, and with all thy Soul.</hi> 1 John 5.3. <hi>This is the love of God, that we keep his Commandments.</hi> 1 John 4.20. <hi>If a Man ſay, I love God, and hateth his Brother, he is a liar.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>How do you prove from Scripture, that we must not only know him whom God hath ſent, but alſo love him as ſuch?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I prove it from <hi>John</hi> 8.42. <hi>Jeſus ſaid unto them, If God were your Father, ye would love me, for I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded forth, and came from God; neither came I of my ſelf, but he ſent me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>How does our love to him
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:60817:10"/>whom God hath ſent, manifest and diſcover it ſelf?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Our love to him whom God hath ſent, diſcovers it ſelf, in our keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Commandments, which require us to truſt in him, and live to him, as one whom God hath ſent to be the Saviour of the World.</p>
            <p>[John 14.15. <hi>If ye love me, keep my Commandments.</hi> Verſ. 21. <hi>He that hath my Commandments, and keepeth them, he it is that loveth me.</hi> Verſ. 23. <hi>If a Man love me, he will keep my Words.</hi> Verſ. 24. <hi>He that lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth me not, keepeth not my ſayings: the Word which ye hear is not mine, but my Fathers which ſent me.</hi> 1 John 2.3, <hi>&amp;c. And hereby we do know that we know him, if we keep his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments. He that ſaith, I know him, and keepeth not his Commandments, is a liar, and the Truth is not in him. But whoſo keepeth his Word, in him verily is the love of God perfected: Hereby know we that we are in him.</hi>]</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>Tell me now what you intend by the Acknowledgment of God, and of Chriſt, which you have mentioned?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> By the Acknowledgment of God and Chriſt, I intend nothing
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:60817:10"/>elſe, but that Love now ſpoken of, as manifeſted by the keeping of God's Commandments.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>Why do you call this an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgment of God and of Chriſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I ſo call it, becauſe they who thus keep the Commandments of God, do indeed acknowledg and confeſs, That he who ſent Jeſus Chriſt is the only true God, and that Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt is he whom God hath ſent.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>Does the Holy Scripture ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs it in the ſame way and manner?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Yes; and in many places.</p>
            <p>[<hi>Col.</hi> 1.10. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.13. <hi>Col.</hi> 2.2. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.4. Ch. 4.3. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.25. <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.1. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.2, 3. <hi>Prov.</hi> 3.6. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.13. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.23. <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.9, 10. 1 <hi>King.</hi> 8.33. <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.32. 1 <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.16. <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.1. Ch. 4.14. Ch. 10.23.]</p>
            <p>Queſt. You ſaid, as I remember, in your firſt Anſwer, That <hi>the best and chiefest thing we are to learn, is the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine that teacheth us to know God, and Jeſus Christ: But why ſaid you ſo?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I ſaid, that the Doctrine
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:60817:11"/>which teacheth us to know God, and Jeſus Chriſt, is the beſt and chiefeſt thing we are to learn, for this Reaſon; Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe this Doctrine which is Truth, revealeth to us the Promiſe of Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Life, and directeth us in the way and means of obtaining this Eternal Life.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>How prove you this?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I prove it from the words of our Saviour, which we have now been diſcourſing of, namely, <hi>This is Eternal Life, that Men may know thee the only true God, and Jeſus Christ whom thou hast ſent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>What do you gather from theſe words?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Firſt, I gather from them, that the Doctrine of Chriſt is a Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine concerning Eternal Life *.</p>
            <p>Secondly; That to know the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the only true God, and Jeſus Chriſt whom he hath ſent, is that which is required of us, for obtaining Eternal Life |.</p>
            <p>Theſe things are clearly and plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifully
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:60817:11"/>witneſſed in the Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</p>
            <p>[* 1 John 5.11. <hi>And this is the Record that God hath given to us Eternal Life, and this Life is in his Son.</hi> John 12.50. <hi>And I know that his Commandment is Life Everlaſting.</hi> John 6.68. <hi>Then</hi> Simon Peter <hi>anſwered him, Lord, to whom ſhall we go? Thou haſt the words of Eternal Life.</hi> 2 Tim. 1.10. <hi>Our Saviour, Jeſus Chriſt, hath aboliſhed Death, and hath brought Life and Immortality to light, through the Goſpel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>| 1 John 2.24, 25. <hi>Let that therefore abide in you, which ye have heard from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning: If that which ye have heard from the beginning ſhall remain in you, ye ſhall continue in the Son, and in the Father. And this is the Promiſe that he hath promiſed us, even Eternal Life.</hi> James 1.12. <hi>Bleſſed is the Man that endureth temptation; for when he is tried, he ſhall receive the Crown of Life, which the Lord hath promiſed to them that love him.</hi> 1 Cor. 2.9, 10. <hi>Eye hath not ſeen, nor Ear heard, neither have entered into the Heart of Man, the things which God hath prepared for them that love him. But God hath revealed them unto us by his Spirit.</hi> 1 Pet. 1.8, 9. <hi>Whom</hi> (to wit, Jeſus Chriſt) <hi>having not ſeen, ye love; in whom though now ye ſee him not, yet believing,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:60817:12"/>ye rejoice with joy unſpeakable and full of glory, receiving the end of your Faith, even the Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of your Souls.</hi> 1 Cor. 16.22. <hi>If any Man love not the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, let him be Anathema Maranatha.</hi> 1 Theſſ. 1.8. <hi>The Lord Jeſus ſhall take vengeance of them that know not God, and that obey not the Goſpel of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> 2 Pet. 1.2. <hi>Grace and Peace be multiplied unto you, through the knowledg</hi> (or acknowledgment) <hi>of God, and of Jeſus our Lord.</hi>]</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>What do you conclude of hence?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I hence conclude, That there is nothing in the World we ſhould ſo eſteem of, and glory in, as the knowledg of God and of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>[Jer. 9.23, 24. <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord, Let not the wiſe Man glory in his Wiſdom, neither let the mighty Man glory in his Might: let not the rich Man glory in his Riches; but let him that glorieth, glory in this, that he under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandeth and knoweth me, that I am the Lord which exerciſe Loving-kindneſs, Judgment and Righteouſneſs in the Earth; for in theſe things I delight, ſaith the Lord.</hi> Phil. 3.7, 8. <hi>What things were gain to me, thoſe I counted loſs for Chriſt; yea, doubtleſs I count
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:60817:12"/>all things but loſs, for the excellency of the knowledg of Chriſt Jeſus my Lord, for whom I have ſuffered the loſs of all things, and do count them but dung, that I may win Chriſt,</hi> &amp;c.]</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="part">
            <head>The Second Part.</head>
            <head type="sub">Treating of Religion in the General, and more particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly of the <hi>Chriſtian Religion.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <p>Q. YOu having now in the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral ſhewed the more neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry things, contained in the beſt of Doctrines, I am willing to hear from you ſomewhat a more particular (yet brief) account of the ſame matters; to wit, as concerning God as conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:60817:13"/>in Himſelf, and in his Works: But firſt I will ask you, <hi>What kind of Knowledg we may have concerning theſe things here in this Life?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> That we may here have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning God, conſidered in Himſelf and in his Works, ſuch a knowledg as is true and ſufficient, hath been al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready proved; but a perfect know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of God, in himſelf, and in his Works, is not here in this Life attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able.</p>
               <p>[1 Cor. 13.9, &amp;c. <hi>We know in part, and we propheſy in part: but when that which is perfect is come, then that which is in part ſhall be done away. When I was a Child I ſpake as a Child, I underſtood as a Child, I thought as a Child: but when I became a Man, I put a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way childiſh things. For now we ſee through a glaſs darkly, but then face to face: Now I know in part, but then ſhall I know, even as alſo I am known.</hi> Job 11.7, &amp;c. <hi>Canſt thou by ſearching find out God? Canſt thou find out the Almighty unto perfection? It is as high as Heaven,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>See</hi> Job 36.26, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Pſal. 77.19. <hi>Thy way is in the Sea, and thy Path in the great Waters, and thy footſteps are well known. See</hi> Pſal. 36.5, 6. Eccleſ. 3.11.
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:60817:13"/>
                  <hi>No Man can find out the Work that God maketh from the beginning to the end. See</hi> Job 37.5. Rom. 11.33. <hi>How unſearchable are the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God, and his Ways paſt finding out.</hi>]</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What are you taught from the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scriptures concerning God, conſidered in himſelf?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Holy Scriptures teach me, concerning God, conſidered in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, theſe two things, namely, That God is one, and that God is a Spirit.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Where do the Scriptures affirm, That God is one?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Scriptures do in many pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces expreſly affirm, that God is <hi>One,</hi> or that there is <hi>one God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>[1 Tim. 2.5. <hi>There is one God, and one Mediator between God and Men, the Man Chriſt Jeſus.</hi> Epheſ. 4.6. <hi>One God and Father of all, who is above all, and through all, and in you all. See</hi> Deut. 6.4. <hi>with</hi> Mark 12.29. Mal. 2.10. Matth. 19.17. Rom. 3.30. 2 Cor. 8.4.6. Jam. 2.19. Zech. 14.9.]</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What are we to underſtand by this, That there is one God?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> By this; That there is one God; or, That God is One; we are
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:60817:14"/>to underſtand, that He alone, or He <hi>only</hi> is God, and that there is no other that hath the ſame Being, or the ſame Kingdom as he hath.</p>
               <p>[It is affirmed in the Scriptures, that <hi>JEHOVAH,</hi> (which is the Name of God, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 83.18. <hi>Jer.</hi> 16.21. <hi>Exod.</hi> 15.3.) is God alone. Pſalm. 86.10. <hi>Thou art great, and doſt wondrous things; Thou art God alone.</hi> See 2 King. 19.15. Iſa. 37.16. Neh. 9.6. <hi>That he only is God,</hi> 2 King. 19.19. <hi>Thou art the Lord God, even thou only.</hi> Iſa. 37.20. That he is the <hi>only true God.</hi> John 17.3. <hi>ſee</hi> Jude <hi>v.</hi> 4. That <hi>there is no God elſe.</hi> Iſa. 46.9. <hi>Remember the former things of old; for I am God, and there is none elſe; I am God, and there is none like me. See</hi> 1 Kings 8.6. That <hi>there is no God beſides him.</hi> Iſa. 44.6. <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord, the King of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>and his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer, the Lord of Hoſts, I am the Firſt, and I am the Laſt, and beſides me there is no God.</hi> Verſ. 8. <hi>Is there a God beſides me? Yea, there is no God, I know not any.</hi> Iſa. 45.5. <hi>I am the Lord, there is none elſe, there is no God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides me. See</hi> Verſ. 6, 14, 21, 22. 1 King. 8.60. Deut. 4.35. 1 Chron. 17.20. <hi>That there is no other God.</hi> Exod. 34.14. <hi>That there is no God with him,</hi> Deut. 32.39. 2 King. 5.15. <hi>Who is God, ſave the Lord?</hi> 2 Sam. 22.32. Pſal. 18.31. <hi>That there is no other
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:60817:14"/>God but one.</hi> 1 Cor. 8.4. <hi>Therefore we muſt have before him no other God.</hi> Exod. 20.3. <hi>Nor worſhip another God.</hi> Exod. 34.14. Pſal. 16.4. &amp; 81.9. <hi>But we are to worſhip</hi> Jehovah, <hi>and ſerve him only.</hi> Exod. 22.20. Mat. 4.10.]</p>
               <p>Q. Why in your Anſwer were thoſe words added, <hi>That there is no other that hath the ſame Being, or the ſame Kingdom as he hath?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> They were added, to ſhew more diſtinctly and expreſly, that God is <hi>alone</hi> both in his Being and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and that there is no other that hath with him, either the ſame Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, or the ſame Majeſty and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority.</p>
               <p>[By the Being and Kingdom of God we here intend the ſame which the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> in <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.20. expreſſeth thus; <hi>His eternal Power and Godhead.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe things are plainly held forth in the Holy Scriptures.</p>
               <p>Firſt; God as to his Being or Nature is <hi>One</hi> or <hi>Alone.</hi> What he is in this reſpect no other is. He is therefore ſaid to be <hi>One Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hovah,</hi> or Lord, <hi>Deut.</hi> 6.4. <hi>Mark</hi> 12.29. Hence is that ſaying of Chriſt to the young
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:60817:15"/>Man that called him, <hi>Good Maſter. Why</hi> (ſaith Jeſus) <hi>calleſt thou me Good? There is none good but One, that is, God,</hi> Mat. 19.16, 17. For the ſame God is ſaid to <hi>be only wiſe,</hi> Rom. 16.27. 1 Tim. 1.17. Jud. <hi>v.</hi> 25. and <hi>alone to have Immortality,</hi> 1 Tim. 6.16.</p>
               <p>Secondly; God in reſpect of his Kingdom and Government, is <hi>One</hi> or <hi>Alone,</hi> There is no other that is ſuch a King, Lord, or Governor as he. Deut. 32.39. <hi>See now,</hi> (ſaith the Lord) <hi>that I, even I am he, and there is no God with me: I kill, and I make a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live; I wound, and I heal: neither is there any that can deliver out of my hand.</hi> 1 Tim. 6.15. <hi>He is the only Potentate.</hi> Jam. 4.12. <hi>There is one Law-giver who is able to ſave, and to deſtroy.</hi> Pſal. 72.18. <hi>Bleſſed be the Lord God, the God of</hi> Iſrael; <hi>who only doth won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drous things.</hi> Iſa. 43.11. <hi>I, even I am the Lord, and beſide me there is no Saviour.</hi> See Hoſ. 13.4. 1 Cor. 12.6. <hi>It is the ſame God that worketh all in all.</hi> In both re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects God teſtifies of him, That there is none like unto him, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 46.9. Thus the Saints have profeſt concerning him. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.2. <hi>There is none holy as the Lord; for there is none beſide thee: neither is there any Rock like our God.</hi> Exod. 15.11. <hi>Who is like unto thee among the Gods?</hi> [or mighty Ones] <hi>who is like thee, glorious in Holineſs, fearful in Praiſes,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:60817:15"/>doing Wonders?</hi> See Exod. 8.10. Deut. 32.26. 1 King. 8.23. Pſal. 35.10. &amp; 86.8. &amp; 89.8. &amp; 113.5. Mich. 7.18.]</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Are not ſome others, even in a good ſenſe, called Gods in the Holy Scriptures?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Yes; both Angels and Men. And indeed ſome of both may not only be called Gods, but alſo may in a good ſenſe be Gods, but not in that ſenſe as the Lord our God is.</p>
               <p>[1 Cor. 8.4, 5, 6. <hi>We know that an Idol is nothing in the World, and that there is none other God but one. For though there be that are called Gods, whether in Heaven or in Earth, (as there be Gods many, and Lords many) but to us there is but [one God] the Father, of whom are all things, and we in</hi> [for] <hi>him, and one Lord Jeſus Chriſt, by whom are all things, and we by him.</hi>]</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>But who are they that in a good ſenſe may be called Gods?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> They in a good ſenſe may be called Gods, firſt, who in ſome Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment are inſtead of God: Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, They who in Government are the Sons of God.</p>
               <p>[Such, both Men and Angels, who in ſome Imployment from God, are to others
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:60817:16"/>inſtead of God, may be called by the very Name of the moſt high God. As for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance; in Exod. 7.1. <hi>The Lord ſaith to</hi> Moſes, <hi>See I have made thee a God</hi> [Elohim] <hi>to</hi> Pharaoh; that is, inſtead of God, as it is expreſt in <hi>Exod.</hi> 4.16. <hi>The Angel of the Lord appeared unto</hi> Moſes <hi>in the flame of a Fire out of the midſt of a Buſh; Exod.</hi> 3.2. This An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel is called, in <hi>verſ.</hi> 4. <hi>Jehovah,</hi> and <hi>Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>him;</hi> or, as we engliſh it, <hi>The Lord and God.</hi> Alſo they who in Government over others are the Sons of the moſt High, are called <hi>Gods. See</hi> Pſal. 82.1, 6. <hi>God ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in the Congregation of the Mighty: he judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth among the Gods.—I have ſaid, Ye are Gods; and [even] all of you are Children</hi> [Sons] <hi>of the moſt High.</hi> John 10.32, &amp;c. <hi>Jeſus anſwered them, Many good Works have I ſhewed you from my Father; for which of theſe Works do ye ſtone me? The Jews anſwered him, ſaying, For a good Work we ſtone thee not, but for Blaſphemy, becauſe that thou being a Man, makeſt thy ſelf God. Jeſus anſwered them, Is it not written in your Law, I ſaid, Ye are Gods? If he called them Gods, unto whom the Word of God came, and the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture cannot be broken: Say ye of him whom the Father hath ſanctified and ſent into the World, Thou blaſphemeſt; becauſe I ſaid, I am the Son of God?</hi> In <hi>Pſal.</hi> 8.5. we read
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:60817:16"/>thus; <hi>Thou haſt made him a little lower than the Angels:</hi> In the <hi>Hebr.</hi> 'tis, <hi>than the Gods.</hi> Here, and in the like places, a ſingle Perſon is not <hi>Elohim,</hi> but <hi>Eloah,</hi> which is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times uſed of the moſt High; as in <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 18.32. <hi>Job</hi> 12.4.</p>
               <p>Now the great God is in diſtinction from theſe, ſometimes called, The <hi>God of Gods,</hi> and <hi>Lord of Lords,</hi> Deut. 10.17. Joſh. 22.22. Pſal. 136.2. Dan. 11.36. (Chap. 2.42.) <hi>And he is ſaid to be greater than all Gods, and above all Gods,</hi> Pſal. 135.5. <hi>He is alſo ſaid to be high above all the Earth, and exalted far above all Gods,</hi> Pſalm. 97.9. He is called, <hi>The high God,</hi> Pſalm. 78.35, 56. <hi>The moſt High,</hi> Numb. 24.16. Deut. 32.8. 2 Sam. 22.14. Dan. 4 17. and elſewhere often; and in <hi>Acts</hi> 7.48. <hi>The moſt High God,</hi> Gen. 14.18. Heb. 7.1. and elſewhere often. <hi>The Lord the moſt high God,</hi> Gen. 14.22. <hi>The Lord moſt High,</hi> Pſal. 47.2. <hi>In</hi> Pſal. 83.18. <hi>That Men may know, that thou whoſe Name alone is JEHOVAH, art the moſt High over all the Earth.</hi> See <hi>Dan.</hi> 5.21. In the place now quoted, the ſame word is rendred, <hi>High,</hi> and <hi>moſt High.</hi>]</p>
               <p>Q. You ſaid, <hi>That God is a Spirit; How prove you that?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Jeſus Chriſt himſelf hath
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:60817:17"/>taught us, That God is a Spirit, <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.24.</p>
               <p>[<hi>Jeſus ſaith unto the Woman of</hi> Sama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria, <hi>Woman, believe me, the hour cometh, when ye ſhall neither in this Mountain, nor yet at</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>worſhip the Father; ye worſhip ye know not what. We know what we worſhip; for Salvation is of the Jews. But the hour cometh, and now is, when the true Worſhippers ſhall worſhip the Father in Spirit, and in Truth; for the Father ſeeketh ſuch to worſhip him. God is a Spirit, and they that worſhip him, muſt worſhip him in Spirit and in Truth,</hi> John 4.21, 22, 23, 24.]</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What muſt we underſtand by this, That God is a Spirit?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> By this, That God is a Spirit, we muſt underſtand two things in the general: Firſt, That God is more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent than all things. Secondly, That the Spirit of Man may be unto us in ſome manner, a Shadow of God.</p>
               <p>[Although Method challengeth this place for the confirmation of this, That God is ſaid to be a Spirit, in way of allu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to the Spirit of Man; yet the proof of it ſhall be reſerved for the cloſe of this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe concerning God, as conſider'd in
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:60817:17"/>himſelf, where it may be done more eaſily, and in fewer words.</p>
               <p>The Excellency of God is diverſly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in the Holy Scriptures. In 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.17. He is called, <hi>The Excellent Glory.</hi> In the Scripture there is aſcribed to God, <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency,</hi> Deut. 33.26. Job 13.11. Ch. 37.4. Pſal. 68.34. Iſa. 35.2. <hi>Greatneſs of Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency,</hi> Exod. 15.7. He is ſaid to be <hi>excellent in Power,</hi> Job 37.23. <hi>More excellent than the Mountains of Prey,</hi> Pſal. 76.4. <hi>O Lord our God, how excellent is thy Name in all the Earth! who haſt ſet thy Glory above the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens,</hi> Pſal. 8.1. <hi>Let them praiſe the Name of the Lord, for his Name alone is excellent. His Glory is above the Earth and Heaven,</hi> Pſal. 148.13. In the ſame ſence he is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, <hi>the great God,</hi> Tit. 2.13. Rev. 19.17. Dan. 2.45. Jer. 32.19. <hi>Great is the Lord, and greatly to be praiſed; and his greatneſs is unſearchable,</hi> Pſal. 145.3. <hi>There is none like to the God of</hi> Jeſurun, <hi>Deut.</hi> 33.26. <hi>And</hi> Solomon <hi>ſaid, Lord God of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>there is no God like thee, in Heaven above, or on Earth beneath,</hi> 1 King. 8.23. <hi>All Nations before the Lord are as nothing, and they are counted to him leſs than nothing and vanity. To whom then will ye liken God? or, what likeneſs will ye compare unto him?—To whom then will ye liken me? Or ſhall I be equal, ſaith the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:60817:18"/>Holy One?</hi> Iſa. 40.17, 18, 25. <hi>To whom will ye liken me, and make me equal, and compare me, that we may be like?</hi> Iſa. 46.5. <hi>Who in the Heaven can be compared unto the Lord? Who among the Sons of the Mighty can be like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned unto the Lord?</hi> Pſal. 89.6. <hi>As the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens are higher than the Earth, ſo are my ways higher than your ways, and my thoughts than your thoughts,</hi> Iſa. 55.9. <hi>But will God in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed dwell on the Earth? Behold, the Heaven, and the Heaven of Heavens cannot contain thee, how much leſs this Houſe that I have builded?</hi> 1 King. 8.27. <hi>See</hi> Jer. 23.23, 24. Acts 7.49.</p>
               <p>But how may we gather that God is thus excellent from his being called a Spirit? Thus; Jeſus Chriſt here diſcovers the Divine Nature, by the moſt excellent thing that is vulgarly known, to wit, the Spirit of Man: Hereby he plainly ſignifies the Excellency of God. And in that he diſcovers this Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency, not as it is in it ſelf, but by a Sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, he clearly intimates, that this Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of God is ſuch, and ſo exceeding great, that we now cannot perceive the ſame, as it is in it ſelf, being far above the preſent ſtrength of our Underſtanding, and way of Knowledg.</p>
               <p>The like we are to obſerve in many other ſcriptural forms of Speech, concerning ſome
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:60817:18"/>things that are Spiritual, and thoſe things that pertain to another World. See <hi>John</hi> 3.10, 11, 12. It was ſaid, That the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Man may be unto us in ſome manner, a Shadow of God. It is neceſſary thus to conceive, for otherwiſe, the term <hi>Spirit</hi> would here ſignifie nothing at all: for it cannot be taken in its proper ſignification here, and can in no other be accepted, but in that we call Metaphorical.]</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Whence does it appear that God is more excellent than all things?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It appears that God is more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent than all things: Firſt, From his Almightineſs. Secondly, From his Eternity. Thirdly, From his Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs or Bleſſedneſs. For the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures declare him to be Almighty, and to be Eternal, and to be Happy or Bleſſed.</p>
               <p>[God is called by the Name of <hi>The Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty,</hi> Job 40.1, 2. <hi>Moreover, the Lord an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered</hi> Job <hi>and ſaid; Shall he that contendeth with the Almighty, inſtruct him? He that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proveth God, let him anſwer it,</hi> Job 37.23. <hi>Touching the Almighty, we cannot find him out; he is excellent in Power and in Judgment, and in plenty of Juſtice.</hi> So elſewhere often.</p>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:60817:19"/>
               <p>He is alſo called, <hi>The Almighty God,</hi> Gen. 17.1. <hi>I am the Almighty God.</hi> And elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where often alſo, <hi>The Lord Almighty,</hi> 2 Cor. 6.18. <hi>And I will be a Father unto you, and ye ſhall be my Sons and Daughters, ſaith the Lord Almighty.</hi> Alſo, <hi>The Lord God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty,</hi> Rev. 21.22. <hi>And I ſaw no Temple therein; for the Lord God Almighty, and the Lamb, are the Temple of it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He is called the <hi>Eternal God,</hi> Deut. 33.27. and the <hi>Everlaſting God,</hi> Gen. 21.33. Rom. 16.26. See <hi>Iſa.</hi> 57.15. Both his Almighti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Eternity are mentioned together; Rev. 4.8. <hi>They ſaid, Holy, holy, holy, Lord God Almighty, which was, and is, and is to come.</hi> Alſo in other places he is called, <hi>The happy or bleſſed God,</hi> 1 Tim. 1.11. <hi>The happy, or bleſſed Potentate,</hi> 1 Tim. 6.15.]</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What are we to conceive by this, That God is Almighty?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> By this, that God is Almighty, we are to conceive, that God needeth not any thing; that he can do every thing, which is neither wicked nor unequal; that he does whatſoever he pleaſeth, and is one, of whom, by whom, and for whom are all things.</p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:60817:19"/>
               <p>[Acts 17.24, 25. <hi>God that made the World, and all things therein, ſeeing that he is Lord of Heaven and Earth, dwelleth not in Temples made with hands: Neither is worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped with Mens hands, as though he needed any thing, ſeeing he giveth to all life, and breath, and all things.</hi> Job 22.1, &amp;c. <hi>Can Man be profitable unto God?</hi> &amp;c. Job 42.1, 2. <hi>Then</hi> Job <hi>anſwered the Lord, and ſaid, I know that thou canſt do every thing, and that no thought of thine can be hindred.</hi> Matth. 3.9. <hi>God is able of theſe Stones to raiſe up Children unto</hi> Abraham. Luke 1.37. <hi>With God no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is impoſſible.</hi> Mat. 19.26. <hi>With God all things are poſſible.</hi> Here underſtand things that are not wicked, nor unequal: <hi>For it is impoſſible for God to lie,</hi> Heb. 6.18. <hi>He cannot lie,</hi> Tit. 1.2. <hi>He cannot deny him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf,</hi> 2 Tim. 2.13. <hi>Far be it from God that he ſhould do wickedneſs, and from the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty, that he ſhould commit Iniquity: for the Work of a Man ſhall he render unto him, and cauſe every Man to find according to his ways. Yea ſurely God will not do wickedly, neither will the Almighty pervert Judgment,</hi> Job 34.10, 11, 12. <hi>God cannot be tempted with evil, neither tempteth he any Man,</hi> Jam. 1.13. <hi>ſee</hi> Pſal. 5.4. 1 Chron. 29.17. <hi>God does whatſoever he pleaſeth.</hi> Pſalm. 115.3. <hi>Our God is in Heaven, he hath done whatſoever he
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:60817:20"/>pleaſed.</hi> Pſal. 135.6. <hi>Whatſoever the Lord pleaſed, that did he in Heaven and in Earth, and in the Seas, and in all deep places.</hi> Iſa. 46.10. <hi>My Counſel ſhall ſtand, and I will do all my pleaſure. Iſa.</hi> 48.14. Hear the words of <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> concerning God; <hi>All the Inhabitants of the Earth are reputed as nothing: and the moſt High doth according to his Will in the Armies of Heaven, and among the Inhabitants of the Earth: and none can ſtay his hand, or ſay unto him, What doſt thou?</hi> Dan. 4.25. <hi>See</hi> Iſa. 55.11. <hi>God is he, of whom, by whom, and for whom are all things,</hi> Rom. 11.36. 1 Cor. 11.12. 2 Cor. 5.18. Heb. 2.10.]</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What are we to conceive by this, That God is Eternal?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> By this, That God is Eternal, we are to conceive, that God is from everlaſting to everlaſting, and always the ſame.</p>
               <p>[Pſal. 90.2. <hi>Before the Mountains were brought forth, or ever thou hadſt formed the Earth and the World; even from everlaſting to everlaſting thou art God. See</hi> Iſa. 43.10. &amp; 44.6. &amp; 48.12. and elſewhere. He is from Everlaſting, or from Eternity; or, as we expreſs it, without beginning: Pſal. 93.2. <hi>Thou art from Everlaſting.</hi> In this
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:60817:20"/>ſenſe he is called, The Everlaſting God; Iſa. 40.28. <hi>He is to Everlaſting,</hi> or to Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity; or, as we expreſs it, without Ending: <hi>He ſhall endure for ever,</hi> Pſalm. 102.13. <hi>See</hi> Pſal. 92.8. Hence he is ſaid to be <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncorrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible,</hi> Rom. 1.23. <hi>Immortal,</hi> 1 Tim. 1.17. and <hi>alone to have Immortality,</hi> 1 Tim. 6.16. <hi>He is always the ſame,</hi> Pſal. 102.26, 27. Heb. 1.11, 12.—<hi>They ſhall periſh, but thou ſhalt endure; yea all of them ſhall wax old like a Garment,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>But thou art the ſame, and thy Years ſhall have no end.</hi> Jam. 1.17. <hi>With the Father of Lights is no variableneſs, neither ſhadow of turning.</hi> Mal. 3.6. <hi>I am the Lord, I change not.</hi>]</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What may we conceive by this, That God is Happy or Bleſſed?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> By this, That God is Happy or Bleſſed, we may conceive that God hath full and eternal Satisfaction, Joy, and Pleaſure in his own Self, and in his own Works.</p>
               <p>Q. You having now ſpoken of the firſt Reaſon, Why God is ſaid to be a Spirit, namely, Becauſe he is more excellent than all things, it remains that you ſpeak of the ſecond Reaſon, which was this, Becauſe the Spirit of
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:60817:21"/>Man may be unto us, in ſome manner, a ſhadow of God; whence we may have ſomewhat a more particular con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception of him: Wherefore I now ask you, <hi>In what the Spirit of Man may be unto us, in ſome manner, a ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of God?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Spirit of Man may be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us, in ſome manner, a ſhadow of God, in that we may thence conceive, in ſome manner, what God is not, and what he is.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What do you thence conceive, That God is not?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> I thence conceive, That God is not more than One, and that God is not viſible; for the Spirit of Man is but one, and is not viſible.</p>
               <p>[Concerning God, as being but One, we have already ſpoken.</p>
               <p>He is not viſible, therefore called, <hi>The Inviſible God,</hi> Col. 1.15. 1 Tim. 1.17. His Eternal Power and Godhead are ſaid to be the Inviſible things of God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.20. He is ſaid to dwell in the Light which no Man can approach unto, and to be one, whom no Man hath ſeen, nor can, ſee
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:60817:21"/>1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.16. It is ſaid, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.27. <hi>That</hi> Moſes <hi>ſaw him that was Inviſible:</hi> that is, He ſaw God by the Eyes of his Mind, who was not to be ſeen by the Eyes of his Body. But it is ſaid of ſome, That they have <hi>ſeen God face to face,</hi> as in <hi>Gen.</hi> 32.30. <hi>Numb.</hi> 14.14. In theſe, and the like places, we muſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, by the Name <hi>God,</hi> an Angel that did repreſent him. This appears by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring <hi>Gen.</hi> 32.30. with <hi>verſ.</hi> 24. and <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 12.4. Thus <hi>Manoah</hi> ſaid to his Wife, concerning him whom he knew to be an Angel of the Lord, <hi>We ſhall ſurely die, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we have ſeen God,</hi> [Elohim.] <hi>Judg.</hi> 13.22. There is a ſeeing of God wherein our happineſs lies, and is attainable only in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther World. <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.8. <hi>Bleſſed are the pure in heart; for they ſhall ſee God.</hi> Then the Sons of God ſhall ſee him as he is, and face to face, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.2. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.12.]</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What do you conceive that God is, from this ſhadow of him the Spirit of Man?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Although we cannot know here, what God is, as he is: yet may we here have ſuch a knowledg of what he is, as is ſufficient for us; and this from the ſhadow of him, the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:60817:22"/>Spirit of Man, conſider'd in its na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Powers, and acquired Vertues.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>But are we after the ſame man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner to conceive of the Divine Nature, as of the Powers and Vertues of an hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Spirit?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> No, in no wiſe; for in all we muſt conſider God, as Almighty, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal, and Happy or Bleſſed, and as one whom we cannot here know as he is.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What after this manner may we conceive of God, from his Shadow, the Spirit of Man?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Powers of a Man's Spirit, endowed with their proper Vertues, may be conſidered in a reſpect to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and outward Actings, and ſo the eternal Power of God may be ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed forth thereby.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What are thoſe Powers of an hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Spirit, which as reſpecting inward Actings, and which as endued with Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, may ſhadow forth unto us the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of God?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Theſe Powers are thoſe which
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:60817:22"/>we commonly call the Underſtanding and the Will.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What do you conceive concerning God, from that in the Spirit of Man, which we call the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> I conceive thence, that God who is Eternal and Almighty, hath Knowledg and Wiſdom, wherein he excelleth all others, as being perfect in both, and having no Inſtructor nor Counſellor with him, but is the giver of all Knowledg and Wiſdom.</p>
               <p>[God hath Knowledg, Wiſdom, and Underſtanding. He is a God of Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg, [or Knowledges] 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.3. See <hi>Pſal.</hi> 139. &amp; <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103.14. With him is Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and Strength; he hath Counſel and Underſtanding, <hi>Job</hi> 12.13. <hi>Rev.</hi> 7.12.</p>
               <p>God excelleth all others in Knowledg and Wiſdom, for he is perfect therein, <hi>Job</hi> 37.16. There is no ſearching of his Underſtanding, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 40.28. <hi>O the depth of the Riches both of the Wiſdom and Knowledg of God!</hi> Rom. 11.33. <hi>He knoweth all things,</hi> 1 Joh. 3.20. <hi>He knoweth the Hearts, and the ſecrets thereof,</hi> 1 Chron. 28.9. Acts 15.8. Pſal. 44.21. <hi>&amp;</hi> 94.11. Luke 16.15. <hi>Times are not hid from the Almighty,</hi> Job 24.1. <hi>He
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:60817:23"/>knoweth not only things preſent, but alſo things paſt, having them in remembrance,</hi> Pſal. 105.8. <hi>Yea things to come,</hi> Iſa. 43.22, 23, 26. <hi>&amp;</hi> 44.7, 8. <hi>&amp;</hi> 48.3, 5, 6, 7, 14, <hi>&amp;c. God hath no In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructor nor Counſellor with him;</hi> that is, the Knowledg and Wiſdom of God are from no other, <hi>Job</hi> 21.22. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 40.13, 14. All the Knowledg and Wiſdom that others have is from God, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 2.26. and elſewhere.]</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What do you conceive concerning God, from that in the Spirit of Man, which we call the Will?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> I conceive thence, That God who is Eternal and Almighty, hath a Will, and ſo, that he can purpoſe, intend, love, hate, and the like, and ſo only as he who is the only Wiſe, Holy, Good, and Righteous God.</p>
               <p>[A Will, and the Act of Willing, is aſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed to God, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.4. <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.4. The Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture mentions the Intents of his Heart, <hi>Jer.</hi> 30.21. and he is often ſaid to purpoſe, to love, to hate, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> He can no otherwiſe purpoſe, and the like, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> than according to his own Nature, who is the only Wiſe, Holy, Good, and Juſt or Righteous God. <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.27. <hi>Rev.</hi> 15.4. <hi>Mat.</hi> 19.17. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 45.21. <hi>He is Light</hi> [that is, moſt Pure, Holy,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:60817:23"/>and Righteous] <hi>and in him is no darkneſs at all,</hi> 1 John 1.5. <hi>He is Love,</hi> that is, moſt Loving, 1 <hi>John</hi> 4.8.]</p>
               <p>Q. You having now ſhewed, That the Eternal Power of God, may in ſome manner be ſhadowed forth, by that Power which the Spirit of Man hath for inward Actings; <hi>Now what do you conceive of God, from that Power which the Spirit of Man hath for out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Actings; for it is the Spirit that gives Life to the Body; and this hath a Power over the Body, and is the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal cauſe of its motions?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> I conceive thence, that the Eternal and Almighty God, hath a Power whereby he is able to do what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever he pleaſeth.</p>
               <p>[Of this Power the Scriptures often ſpeak, as in <hi>Mat.</hi> 22.29. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.4. <hi>Exod.</hi> 9.16. <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.17. <hi>Luke</hi> 12.5. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3.20. And it is there called, <hi>The Word of God, the Breath,</hi> or <hi>Spirit of God, the Hand of God, the Arm of God,</hi> and the like, as in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55.11. <hi>Zech.</hi> 4.6. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89.13. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 50.2.</p>
               <p>By this Power God is able to do whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he will, <hi>Dan.</hi> 3.17. <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.9. <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.21.
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:60817:24"/>
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3.20. <hi>Heb.</hi> 5 7. &amp; 11.19. For God is excellent in Power, <hi>Job</hi> 37.23. <hi>O Lord God of Hoſts, who is a ſtrong Lord like unto thee?</hi> Pſal. 89.8. None is able to withſtand him, 2 <hi>Chron</hi> 20.6. <hi>The Breath of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty hath given me Life,</hi> Job 33.4. <hi>In the Lord Jehovah is everlaſting ſtrength,</hi> Iſa. 26.4. <hi>My Counſel ſhall ſtand, and I will do all my Pleaſure,</hi> Iſa. 46.10.]</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What have you further to ſay concerning God, from this ſhadow of him the Spirit of Man?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> I am taught to add no more, but to conclude, That this God who is a Spirit, is the Living and true God.</p>
               <p>[God is often called <hi>the Living God,</hi> Pſal. 42.2. Mat. 16.16. <hi>The living and true God,</hi> 1 Theſſ. 1.9. Now becauſe the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of this, That God is ſaid to be a Spirit, in alluſion to the Spirit of Man, was reſerved for this place, I ſhall therefore here perform it: And although my Diſcourſe thereof will be contracted to that brevity the Tract in hand does require, yet I hope it will give ſatisfaction to all that are unpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judiced and conſiderate.</p>
               <p>In this ſaying, <hi>God is a Spirit;</hi> the term <hi>Spirit</hi> muſt be udderſtood either properly or improperly; not properly, for ſo it denoteth
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:60817:24"/>Wind, or rather a Blaſt (to wit) of Wind, as the word anſwering it in <hi>Hebrew</hi> is ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 19.7. And thus it is uſed <hi>John</hi> 3.8. <hi>The Wind bloweth where it liſteth.</hi> In an improper ſenſe 'tis not imaginable how it ſhould be accepted, unleſs metapho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rically. And thus it cannot be taken im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately from its primary ſignification; and therefore muſt have reſpect, either to thoſe incorporeal Beings, which from their Office are commonly called <hi>Angels;</hi> or the principal and more noble part of Man, both which are named <hi>Spirits</hi> or <hi>Ghoſts,</hi> as bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſome reſemblance in reſpect of inviſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and might to Blaſts, or Ghoſts, or Guſts of Wind. Now it is altogether un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely, that our Saviour, eſpecially in ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to a Woman of <hi>Samaria,</hi> ſhould in this term <hi>Spirit,</hi> allude to Angelical Spirits, it being a matter much to be doubted, whether theſe Creatures were at this time known to any in the World (unleſs a few) by the name of Spirits. But however this is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, That ſuch a Metaphor or Compariſon would have been, when uſed by our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, of little or no uſe at all in the World; for that there were any ſuch Beings, that were Spirits or incorporeal Subſtances, was a thing not generally known in the World, and denied by a conſiderable Party among
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:60817:25"/>the Jews themſelves: for, as we read <hi>Acts</hi> 23.8. <hi>The Sudduces ſay, That there is no Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, neither Angel nor Spirit;</hi> That is to ſay, no Angel which is a Spirit, or incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poreal Subſtance: For 'tis not imaginable that the <hi>Sadduces,</hi> who owned the five Books of <hi>Moſes,</hi> ſhould deny that there were any Angels, there being in thoſe Writings ſo evident and frequent mention of them: but 'tis eaſily conceivable, that they might deny Angels to be incorporeal, in that the Hiſtory of <hi>Moſes</hi> does often ſpeak of their appearance with Bodies, like unto Men: But that which fully and clearly determines the Matter, is that which follows in the Text; namely theſe words, <hi>but the Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees confeſs both.</hi> Whence it appears that the preceeding words contain in them no more than two things denied by the <hi>Sadduces,</hi> which cannot be, unleſs my Interpretation be admitted: for they muſt needs be three, if we diſtinguiſh betwixt <hi>Angel</hi> and <hi>Spirit,</hi> as different Subjects; as any may reckon that can but tell three; for <hi>Reſurrection, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel,</hi> and <hi>Spirit,</hi> muſt needs be three. My Expoſition may alſo be defended from that which follows in <hi>verſ.</hi> 9. and from the Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurdities which will follow the denial of it. But to return, I ſay, That if our Saviour, by the term <hi>Spirit,</hi> intended an alluſion to
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:60817:25"/>Angels, the word would import little or no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at all; For what could Men conceive thence concerning God? That he is not corporeal? Be it ſo. Notwithſtanding this is certain, that ſome would not thence ſo conceive; and that at leaſt the Woman of <hi>Samaria,</hi> and others of the vulgar ſort, could hardly, if at all, find any ſuch docu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the ſimilitude. But what elſe could Men from this Metaphor learn concerning God? Little elſe upon any clear and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted evidence, the nature of theſe Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits being ſo little known by the wiſeſt of Men. Surely our Saviour intended in this Metaphor, a clear and plentiful inſtruction concerning God, and for the uſe of the vulgar ſort. Whence I conclude, that Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus has not reſpect here to Angelical Spirits in this Compariſon, but to the Spirit of Man. In this ſenſe the Compariſon is ſuited to vulgar Capacities: for there is no Man but experimentally knows that he has a Spirit. And there is nothing vulgarly known in the whole Creation of God, that does excel, or may be equal to humane Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits. And moreover, this noble part of Man paſſeth commonly under this name of <hi>Spirit.</hi> How fruitful of inſtruction the Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude is, as thus underſtood, hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready in ſome meaſure been ſhewed. It
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:60817:26"/>only remains, that I ſhew how well this ſenſe of the term <hi>Spirit</hi> agrees with the Context. This in as few words as may be, thus:</p>
               <p>To what the Woman of <hi>Samaria</hi> ſaid, <hi>verſ.</hi> 20. <hi>Our Fathers worſhipped in this Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, and ye ſay, that in</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>is the place where Men ought to worſhip.</hi> To this, I ſay, our Saviour replies in <hi>verſ.</hi> 21, 22, 23, 24. In this reply we have both a prophetical and doctrinal diſcovery. For in <hi>verſ.</hi> 21. he fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tells the deſtruction of both Temples, that in <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and that alſo in <hi>Samaria,</hi> and the removal of the <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Samaritans</hi> out of their own Countries: So that they ſhould not worſhip in the places about which they contended, what mind ſoever they might have thereunto. <hi>Woman,</hi> ſaith our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, <hi>believe me, the hour cometh when ye ſhall neither in this Mountain, nor yet at</hi> Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, <hi>worſhip the Father.</hi> In the next place our Saviour teacheth the Woman divers things of no mean importance. For in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of former times, and the time preſent he informs her, that in the Controverſy now mentioned, the <hi>Jews</hi> had Truth on their ſide, and the <hi>Samaritans</hi> were in a wrong Opinion, and that not only in reſpect of the place of Worſhip, but alſo in the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of worſhipping. This Jeſus aſſerteth
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:60817:26"/>thus, <hi>verſ.</hi> 22. <hi>Ye worſhip ye know not what;</hi> or, ye know not after what manner ye worſhip; that is, ye <hi>Samaritans</hi> have no good reaſon or ground for your way of worſhipping, but we <hi>Jews</hi> know after what manner we worſhip, having a good ground for worſhipping at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> by offering Sacrifices there, and for the way of worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping. Then our Saviour thus confirmeth it: <hi>for Salvation is of the Jews;</hi> that is, the Doctrine teaching Men ſo to worſhip God as to pleaſe him, and obtain Salvation, is from Prophets that are of the Jewiſh Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. In <hi>verſ.</hi> 23, 24. our Saviour informs the Woman, as to the future time, which was now at hand, theſe two things.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That there muſt be a new kind of Worſhippers, whom he calls <hi>True Worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers,</hi> becauſe typified by, and more excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent than legal Worſhippers; and a new way of worſhipping, to wit, <hi>in Spirit and Truth;</hi> that is to ſay, in ſuch a manner as is different from the legal way, and was ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pified by it, and which therefore is more excellent. This Worſhip the Doctrine of the New Covenant teacheth: for this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine abrogates the legal Form, and does introduce that Worſhip, which the legal Worſhip was a type and ſhadow of. This new Covenant Doctrine is upon this account
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:60817:27"/>called <hi>Spirit</hi> and <hi>Truth,</hi> as the Moſaical Doctrine, in relation to it, is called <hi>the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter;</hi> and is ſaid to have the ſhadow of good things to come, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.6, &amp;c. <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.17. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.1.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Our Saviour ſhews, why ſuch Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippers, and ſuch a way of Worſhip muſt be: This he does firſt barely expreſs in theſe words, <hi>For ſuch the Father ſeeketh to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip him,</hi> verſ. 23. Then he briefly explains it, <hi>verſ.</hi> 24. where he diſcovers;</p>
               <p n="1">1. Why the Father ſeeketh ſuch to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip him. <hi>God is a Spirit.</hi> Therefore now at length, having a mind to diſcover him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf more clearly than in times paſt, he will no longer be worſhipped after the more groſs and carnal way of the Law, but in a more ſpiritual and excellent way, yet in ſuch as was prefigured by the Law. This is to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip in Spirit and Truth, <hi>i.e.</hi> in ſuch a way, as being compared with the legal, does as much differ from it, and excel it, as the Spirit, that is, the ſignification of a Letter differs from, and excels the Letter it ſelf. The like may be ſaid of a Shadow and its Body; ſee <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.29. &amp; 7.6. <hi>Col.</hi> 3.3.</p>
               <p n="2">2. What it is for the Father to ſeek ſuch to worſhip him. To ſeek, is, to command, which is here ſignified by the moral neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty that Men have of worſhipping the Father
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:60817:27"/>in Spirit and Truth. And therefore they that worſhip him, muſt worſhip him in Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit and Truth.</p>
               <p>Now let the Reader judg.]</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> Of God conſidered in his Works of Creation.</head>
               <p>Q. NOw ſeeing we have diſcourſed of God as conſidered in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, we are in the next place to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of him as conſidered in his Works: Wherefore I ſhall firſt ask you, <hi>What are the Works of God?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Works of God we ought to conſider; and althô they are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold, yet they may be ſaid in the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral to be two-fold; namely, His Work of Creation, and his Work of Government.</p>
               <p>[<hi>Job</hi> 37.14, 16. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 7.13. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 77.12. &amp; 46.8. &amp; 111.2. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.20.]</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is God's Work of Creation?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> God's Work of Creation, is
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:60817:28"/>that Work of his, whereby he hath made Heaven, the Heaven of Heavens, with all their Hoſt; the Earth, and all things that are therein; the Seas, and all that is therein.</p>
               <p>[Nehem. 9.6. <hi>See</hi> Gen. 1. Job 38.4, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Pſal. 104.5, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and 136.5, <hi>&amp;c. Thus ſaith the Lord thy Redeemer, and he that formed thee from the Womb, I am the Lord that maketh all things, that ſtretcheth forth the Heavens alone, that ſpreadeth abroad the Earth by my ſelf,</hi> Iſa. 44.24. Act. 4.24. &amp; 14.15. &amp; 17.24. Rev. 10.6. <hi>Thus ſaith God the Lord, he that created the Heavens, and ſtretched them out, he that ſpread forth the Earth, and that which cometh out of it; he that giveth breath unto the People upon it, and Spirit to them that walk therein,</hi> Iſa. 42.5. <hi>See</hi> Iſa. 45.12, 18. Mark 10.6.]</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>In what manner did God create the World, and the things that are therein?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> God by reaſon of his Will and Pleaſure, did in his Wiſdom, by his Power, and for himſelf, make, form, or create in ſix days, all things, and all very good.</p>
               <p>[<hi>He created all things by reaſon of his Will or Pleaſure,</hi> Rev. 4.11. <hi>Thou, O Lord, haſt
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:60817:28"/>created all things, and for</hi> (or by reaſon of) <hi>thy pleaſure, they are and were created.</hi> See alſo before.</p>
               <p>God created them in his Wiſdom. Pſal. 104.24. <hi>O Lord, how manifold are thy Works! in Wiſdom haſt thou made them all.</hi> Prov. 3.19.20. <hi>The Lord by Wiſdom hath founded the Earth; by <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding hath he eſtabliſhed the Heavens; by his Knowledg the Depths are broken up, and the Clouds drop down the Dew,</hi> Pſal. 136.5.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>He hath created all things by his Power.</hi> Jer. 10.12. <hi>He hath made the Earth by his Power; he hath eſtabliſhed the World by his Wiſdom, and hath ſtretched out the Heavens by his Diſcretion.</hi> Jer. 32.17. <hi>Ah Lord God, behold thou haſt made the Heaven and the Earth by thy great Power and ſtretched-out Arm, and there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing too hard for thee;</hi> or, nothing hid from thee. See <hi>Iſa.</hi> 40.26. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.5. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 33.6. <hi>By the Word of the Lord were the Heavens made; and all the Hoſt of them by the breath of his Mouth.</hi> Verſ. 9. <hi>For he ſpake, and it was done; he commanded, and it ſtood faſt. See</hi> Pſal. 148.5. Gen. 1.3. <hi>God ſaid, Let there be Light, and there was Light.</hi> 2 Cor. 4.6. <hi>God commanded the Light to ſhine out of Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</hi> Job 26.13. <hi>By his Spirit he hath gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed the Heavens; his Hand hath formed the crooked Serpent.</hi> Job 33.4. <hi>The Spirit of God
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:60817:29"/>hath made me, and the Breath of the Almighty hath given me Life.</hi> Prov. 16.1. <hi>He made all things for himſelf. He made all things in ſix days, and all very good,</hi> Gen. 1. and Ch. 2.1, 2. Exod. 20.11.]</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What are the principal Creatures that God did make?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The principal Creatures that God did make, are Angels and Men.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What have you learn'd concerning the Creation of Men?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> I have learn'd concerning the creation of Men, That God after he had made all other Creatures, <hi>created Man in his own Image, in the Image of God created he him, Male and Female created he them:</hi> and <hi>that God bleſſed them, and ſaid unto them, Be fruitful and multiply, and repleniſh the Earth, and ſubdue it, and have dominion over the Fiſh of the Sea, and over the Fowl of the Air, and over every living thing that moveth upon the Earth,</hi> Gen. 1.27, 28. Jam. 3.9.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Can you expreſs more diſtinctly the Creation of Men?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:60817:29"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Yes; after this manner. The Lord God created at the firſt only a Man and a Woman, called <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve. For the Lord God formed the Man [of] the Duſt of the Ground, and breathed into his Noſtrils the Breath of Life, and the Man became a living Soul.</hi> Afterwards the Lord God cauſed a deep ſleep to fall upon <hi>Adam,</hi> and he ſlept, and he took one of his Ribs, and cloſed up the Fleſh inſtead thereof. And of the Rib which the Lord God had taken from the Man, made he a Woman, and brought her to the Man to be his Wife, and a meet help unto him. Of theſe two have all others of Mankind deſcended, by that bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, of Multiplying and increaſing, which God gave to <hi>Adam</hi> and his Wife, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.7, 18, 21, 22. and 5.1, 2. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.8, 9. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.13. <hi>Job</hi> 4.17. &amp; 32.22. &amp; 33.6. &amp; 34.19. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 139.13, &amp;c. <hi>Jer.</hi> 1.5. <hi>Zech.</hi> 12.1. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 11.5. <hi>Job</hi> 10.8, &amp;c. and 31.15.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:60817:30"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> Of God's Work of Government in General; and in Special as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating to Angels.</head>
               <p>Q. LEt us now ſpeak of God's Work of Government, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning which I ſhall firſt ask you this Queſtion; <hi>What mean you by God's Work of Government?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> By God's Work of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, I mean, that Work of his, in which by his Power he ruleth and reigneth over all, throughout all Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerations for ever and ever, as Lord of Heaven and Earth, and as a great King above all Gods.</p>
               <p>[God ruleth or reigneth (or does exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe Dominion and Kingſhip) over all. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103.19, &amp;c. <hi>The Lord hath prepared his Throne in the Heavens; and his Kingdom ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth over all. Bleſs the Lord, ye his Angels that excel in ſtrength, that do his Commandments; hearkning to the Voice of his Word. Bleſs the Lord all ye his Hoſts; ye Miniſters of his that do his
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:60817:30"/>pleaſure. Bleſs the Lord, all his Works in all places of his Dominion: Bleſs the Lord, O my Soul. See</hi> Job 25.2, 3. Joſh. 2.11. Iſa. 66.1.</p>
               <p>God by his Power ruleth and reigneth throughout all Generations for ever and ever. Pſal. 66.7. <hi>He ruleth by his Power for ever; his Eyes behold the Nations.</hi> Pſal. 145.13. <hi>Thy Kingdom is an everlaſting Kingdom,</hi> [or a Kingdom of all Ages] <hi>and thy Dominion endureth throughout all Generations.</hi> Pſal. 93.2. <hi>Thy Throne is eſtabliſhed of old, thou art from everlaſting.</hi> Pſal. 10.16. <hi>The Lord is King for ever and ever.</hi> 1 Tim. 1.17. <hi>Now unto the King Eternal, Immortal, Inviſible, the only Wiſe God, be honour and glory for ever and ever.</hi> Amen. <hi>See</hi> Pſal. 29.16. Jer. 10.10. Pſal. 146.10. Dan. 4.3, 34. Jude 25. 1 Cor. 15.24, 28. <hi>Then cometh the end, when he ſhall have delivered up the Kingdom to God, even the Father,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>And when all things ſhall be ſubdued unto him, then ſhall the Son alſo himſelf be ſubject unto him, that put all things under him, that God may be all in all.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>God ruleth and reigneth as Lord of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and Earth, and as a great King above all Gods. Gen. 14.19. <hi>The Poſſeſſor of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and Earth.</hi> Deut. 10.14. <hi>Behold, the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and the Heaven of Heavens is the Lords thy God; the Earth alſo, with all that therein is.</hi> Pſal. 95.3. <hi>The Lord is a great God, and
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:60817:31"/>a great King above all Gods. See</hi> Pſal. 97.9. 1 Chron. 29.11, 12. <hi>Thine, O Lord, is the Greatneſs, and the Power, and the Glory, and the Victory, and the Majeſty; for all that is in the Heaven and in the Earth is thine: thine is the Kingdom, O Lord, and thou art exalted as Head above all. Both Riches and Honour come of thee, and thou reigneſt over all, and in thine hand is power and might, and in thine hand it is to make great, and to give ſtrength unto all.</hi> 1 Cor. 11.3. <hi>But I would have you know that the Head of every Man is Chriſt; and the Head of the Woman is the Man, and the Head of Chriſt is God.</hi> Pſal. 113.4, &amp;c. <hi>The Lord is high above all Nations, and his Glory above the Heavens. Who is like unto the Lord our God, who dwelleth on high? who humbleth himſelf to behold the things that are in Heaven, and in the Earth.</hi> 1 Tim. 6.15. <hi>He is the bleſſed and only Potentate, the King of Kings, and Lord of Lords. See</hi> Pſal. 93. &amp; 97. &amp; 99. Pſal. 24.7. &amp; 145.12. Rev. 19.6. 2 Chron. 20.6.]</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What have you learned more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly touching God's Government in reſpect of Angels?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Touching God's Government in reſpect of Angels, I have learned a few things that are more eaſy and needful to be known: as this in the
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:60817:31"/>general, that part of thoſe Spirits, called <hi>Angels,</hi> having ſinned, God ſpared them not, but caſt them down to Hell, and deliver'd them into Chains of Darkneſs, to be reſerved unto Judgment; but that part of thoſe Spirits abode in the Truth, and are now called <hi>the Holy Angels,</hi> and the like; when the name of <hi>Devils,</hi> and the like, is given to thoſe that ſinned. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.4. <hi>Jude</hi> v. 6. <hi>Joh.</hi> 8.44. <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.17. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.20. <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.31.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What have you learned in ſpecial concerning thoſe Spirits that ſinned not?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Concerning thoſe Spirits that ſinned not, I have learned, that there is an innumerable company of them, and that God hath made them to be his Angels, [that is, Meſſengers] and his Miniſters in the exerciſe of his Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and hath made them all ſubject to Jeſus Chriſt, even thoſe that were among them, Thrones and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions; that is, Kings and Lords. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.22. <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.7. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.22. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.20.</p>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:60817:32"/>
               <p>Q. <hi>What have you learned in ſpecial concerning thoſe Spirits that ſinned?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Concerning thoſe Spirits that ſinned, I have learned, That their number is very great; that one of them is the Prince or Chief, and that the reſt are his Angels. He is called, <hi>The Devil, Satan,</hi> and the like; who as a roaring Lion walketh about ſeeking whom he may devour; but is now under the Power of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>[Mark 5.9. Epheſ. 2.2. Mat. 25.41. Mark 1.13. Mat. 12.28. Heb. 2.8, 14. Phil. 2.9, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The name <hi>Devil</hi> ſignifies a Slanderer, or one that ſeeks to deceive by lies; and <hi>Satan</hi> ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies an Adverſary. See <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.9.]</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> Of God's Government relating to Men, before the ſin of our firſt Parents, and thence to the times wherein Chriſt was raiſed up.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>WHat have you learned more particularly touching God's
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:60817:32"/>Government in reſpect of Men?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Touching God's Government in reſpect of Men, I have learned ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral things, according to its difference in different times; namely, the time before our firſt Parents ſinned, and the times after it.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What have you been taught con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Government of God, as it reſpects the time before our firſt Parents ſinned?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Concerning God's Government as relating to the time before our firſt Parents ſinned, I am taught ſome ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral things; namely, That they had for the place of their abode, the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of <hi>Eden,</hi> which the Man was to dreſs and keep; that they had given to them for Meat, every Herb, and the Fruit of all Trees, except the Tree of the Knowledg of Good and Evil, which God forbad them to eat of: Alſo that they both tranſgreſſed this Commandment; the Woman firſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſeduced by the Serpent, the Devil; then the Man, whom his Wife drew
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:60817:33"/>to eat of the forbidden Fruit. <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. &amp; 2. &amp; 3. Chapters. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.14. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.3.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What have you been taught con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Government of God, as it reſpects the times after our firſt Parents had ſinned?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> I am taught in the general, That when Man had ſinned, and ſo became ſubject to the Judgment of God, then God publiſh'd his Promiſe of Chriſt, whom ſince he hath raiſed up; <hi>and ſince by one Man Sin entred into the World, and Death by Sin, and ſo Death paſſed upon all Men:</hi> The Government of God towards Man is to be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered according to the times in which Chriſt was promiſed, and the times af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his being raiſed up. <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.8, &amp;c. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.19. &amp; 5.12. <hi>Luk.</hi> 1.68, 69, &amp;c. <hi>Acts</hi> 13.23.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What have you been taught touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God's Government towards Men in the times when Chriſt was promiſed?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> I am taught, That the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God did then reſpect Mens
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:60817:33"/>being in the World, and their ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of God therein, and both in a way agreeable to Men that were ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected to a natural Death, and by their ſins liable to eternal Death; and in a way ſuitable to the times before the appearing of our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Jeſus Chriſt, who hath aboliſhed Death, and hath brought Life and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality to light by the Goſpel. <hi>Act.</hi> 17.25, &amp;c. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.12. &amp; 6.23. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.1, 2. 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1.10. <hi>Matth.</hi> 11.20, &amp;c. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.10.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How did this Government of God reſpect the Being of Men in the VVorld?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> This Government did reſpect Mens Being in the World, in that God gave unto them places wherein to live, and ſupplies for the ſuſtaining of their Lives, and the maintaining of good order amongſt them.</p>
               <p>[Gen. 3.23, 24. Deut. 32. Pſalm. 115.16. Act. 17.26. Exod. 23.20. Neh. 9.6. Pſalm. 36.6. Nehem. 9.21. Pſal. 65. &amp; 147. Prov. 24.12. 1 King. 8.45. Job. 10.22. Rom. 13.1, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>]</p>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:60817:34"/>
               <p>Q. <hi>How did this Government of God reſpect Mens ſeeking of God in the World?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> This Government of God did reſpect Mens ſeeking of him, in that he dealt in ſuch a way and manner with them, that they might ſo ſeek him as to find mercy and favour with him. <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.6. <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 105.4. &amp; 14.2. <hi>Act.</hi> 17.27. <hi>Jer.</hi> 29.13, &amp;c. <hi>Jer.</hi> 6.16. <hi>Prov.</hi> 21.21. <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.8. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 33.22. &amp; 63.13. <hi>Nehem.</hi> 1.5. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 25.10. &amp; 32.10. &amp; 86.5. &amp; 103.11. <hi>Prov.</hi> 8.35, 36.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>VVhat is it ſo to ſeek God, as to find mercy and favour with him?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To ſeek God ſo as to find Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and Favour with him, is, To fear God, and to hope in his Mercy.</p>
               <p>[This is variouſly expreſt in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; ſometimes as in the Anſwer. So in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 147.11. <hi>The Lord taketh pleaſure in them that fear him, in thoſe that hope in his Mercy,</hi> Pſal. 33.18. Sometimes more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſely, as in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103.11. <hi>For as the Heaven is high above the Earth; ſo great is his Mercy toward them that fear him:</hi> And in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 33.22. <hi>Let thy Mercy, O Lord, be upon us, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:60817:34"/>as we hope in thee.</hi> It is ſometimes ſet forth by Repentance, <hi>Jer.</hi> 8.6. <hi>Job</hi> 42.6. 1 <hi>King.</hi> 8.47. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 14.6. &amp; 18.30, &amp;c. <hi>Joel</hi> 2.14. Alſo thus, <hi>To turn to the Lord, and to be obedient to his Voice,</hi> Deut. 4.29, 30. <hi>To acknowledg our Offences, and ſeek the face of the Lord,</hi> Hoſ. 5.15. <hi>To return to the Lord and ſeek him,</hi> Hoſ. 7.10. <hi>Sow to your ſelves in Righteouſneſs, reap in Mercy: break up your fallow Ground, for it is time to ſeek the Lord, till he come and rain Righteouſneſs upon you,</hi> Hoſ. 10.12. <hi>See</hi> Prov. 3.1, &amp;c. <hi>If thou do well, ſhalt thou not be accepted?</hi> Gen. 4.7. Noah <hi>found Grace in the Eyes of the Lord.</hi> Noah <hi>was a juſt Man, upright in his Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and walked with God,</hi> Gen. 6.8, 9. <hi>There was a Man in the Land of</hi> Uz <hi>whoſe name was</hi> Job, <hi>and that Man was perfect and upright, and one that feared God, and eſchewed evil,</hi> Job 1.1. <hi>He hath ſhewed thee, O Man, what is Good: and what doth the Lord require of thee, but to do juſtly, and to love mercy, and to walk humbly with thy God?</hi> [or to hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble thy ſelf to walk with thy God] <hi>Mich.,</hi> 6.8. <hi>Then</hi> Peter <hi>opened his Mouth, and ſaid Of a truth I perceive that God is no reſpector of Perſons: But in every Nation, he that feareth him, and worketh Righteouſneſs, is accepted with him,</hi> Act. 10.34, 35. <hi>God will render to every Man according to his Deeds: To them who
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:60817:35"/>by patient continuance in well-doing, ſeek for Glory, and Honour, and Immortality, he will render eternal Life,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11.]</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How did God make known unto Men this way of ſeeking him?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> God by his Works and Word made known unto Men this way of ſeeking him, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Did God, both by his Works and Word, make known unto all Men this way of ſeeking him?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> No; For this way of ſeeking God was made known unto ſome, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by his Works of Creation, and by ſome Works of his in the Government of the World.</p>
               <p>[Pſal. 147.19, 20. <hi>He ſheweth his Words unto</hi> Jacob, <hi>his Statutes and his Judgments unto</hi> Iſrael. <hi>He hath not dealt ſo with any Nation; and as for his Judgments, they have not known them.</hi> Rom. 1.19, <hi>&amp;c. That which may be known of God, was manifeſt in</hi> [among] <hi>them,</hi> [to wit, the Gentiles] <hi>for God hath ſhewed it unto them. For the inviſible Things of him from the Creation of the World are clearly ſeen, being underſtood by the things that are made, even his eternal Power and Godhead, ſo
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:60817:35"/>that they are without excuſe: Becauſe that when they knew God, they glorified him not as God, neither were thankful, &amp;c.</hi> Rom. 2.4. <hi>Or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſeſt thou the riches of his goodneſs, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearance, and long-ſuffering, not knowing that the goodneſs of God leadeth thee to Repentance?</hi> Act. 14.16, 17. <hi>God in times paſt ſuffered all Nations to walk in their own ways. Neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs he left not himſelf without witneſs, in that he did good, and gave us Rain from Heaven, and fruitful Seaſons, filling our Hearts with Food and Gladneſs.</hi>]</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Was there no more made known by the Word of God, then was made known by his Works?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Much more was made known by the Word of God, than was by his Works. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 147.19, 20. &amp; 19.7, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What more was there made known by the Word of God, than by his Works?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Firſt, This Doctrine; That there is forgiveneſs with God, that he may be feared, (which is the ſubſtance of the Doctrine of Chriſt) was more plainly made known by the Word of God, than by his Works. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 130. <hi>Deut.</hi> 34.6, 7. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.1, 2. <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.39, &amp;c.</p>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:60817:36"/>
               <p>Q. <hi>What elſe was made known by the Word of God, that was not by his Works?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Works of Righteouſneſs were more fully made known by the Word of God, than by his Works. <hi>Deut.</hi> 4.5, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Is there any thing elſe wherein the Word of God did excel his Works, in point of Inſtruction?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Yes; For thoſe Ordinances which were ſhadows of good things to come, and were to be done away by Chriſt, were made known only by the Word of God. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 99.7. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.15. <hi>Col.</hi> 2.14, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Where are theſe Ordinances to be found?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Theſe Ordinances are to be found eſpecially in the Law of <hi>Moſes:</hi> for they appertain only to the times of the Old Covenant, wherein Chriſt was promiſed. <hi>Exod.</hi> 18.20. 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 17.37. <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.1, 10.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What mean you by the Old Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> By the Old Covenant, I mean
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:60817:36"/>that Covenant which God made with them, whom he brought out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> to give the Land of <hi>Canaan</hi> to them, I mean the Children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> the Son of <hi>Iſaac,</hi> the Son of <hi>Abraham,</hi> to whom and to whoſe Seed were the Promiſes made. <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.9. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.16.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> Of God's Government ſince Chriſt hath been raiſed up, and particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly of God's raiſing up of Chriſt.</head>
               <p>Q. YOu having ſhew'd a few things (and enough for the preſent) which you have been taught concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God's Government, relating to the times wherein Chriſt was promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: It remains now that we diſcourſe of God's Government in the times ſince Chriſt hath been raiſed up: I ask you therefore, <hi>What have you learned concerning this Divine Government?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Concerning God's Government
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:60817:37"/>ſince the raiſing up of Chriſt, I have learned, That I am firſt and chiefly to mind the Work of God in raiſing up Chriſt, and his Work in ruling by him amongſt Men unto the end of the World.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What have you learned concerning the Work of God in raiſing up Chriſt?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Concerning the Work of God in raiſing up Chriſt, I have learned, That God, according to his Promiſe, raiſed up the Chriſt, even Jeſus, by cauſing him to be born, and to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the Chriſt.</p>
               <p>[Luke 1.68, 69, &amp;c. <hi>Bleſſed be the Lord God of Iſrael, for he hath viſited and redeemed his People: And hath raiſed up an Horn of Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for us, in the Houſe of his Servant</hi> David; <hi>as he ſpake by the Mouth of his Holy Prophets, which have been ſince the World began.</hi> Act. 2.30. <hi>Therefore</hi> David <hi>being a Prophet, and knowing that God hath ſworn with an Oath to him, That of the Fruit of his Loins, according to the Fleſh, he would raiſe up Chriſt to ſit up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his Throne, &amp;c.</hi> Acts 3.26. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto you firſt, God having raiſed up his Son Jeſus, ſent him to bleſs you, in turning every one of you from his Iniquities.</hi> Act. 13.27. Heb. 5.4.5. <hi>And no
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:60817:37"/>Man taketh this honour unto himſelf, but he that is called of God, as was</hi> Aaron. <hi>So alſo Chriſt glorified not himſelf, to be made</hi> [or become] <hi>an High Prieſt: but he</hi> [glorified him] <hi>that ſaid unto him, Thou art my Son, to day have I begotten thee.</hi> Verſ 9. <hi>And being made perfect, he became the Author of eternal Salvation unto all them that obey him.</hi> Acts 2.26. <hi>Therefore let all the Houſe of</hi> Iſrael <hi>know aſſuredly, that God hath made that ſame Jeſus whom ye have crucified, both Lord and Chriſt.</hi>]</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How did God cauſe Jeſus to be born?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> God did cauſe Jeſus to be born, by the Holy Ghoſt coming upon the Virgin, of whom he was born, <hi>Mat.</hi> 1.18. <hi>Luk.</hi> 1.35.</p>
               <p>Q. Tell me by the way, <hi>How is this Jeſus to be known and diſtinguiſhed from all others?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> This Jeſus who in the days of his Fleſh, was by Face known from all others, is now of us to be known and diſtinguiſhed from all others; by that deſcription the Scriptures give us of him, in the Hiſtory of his Birth, Life, Death, Reſurrection from the Dead,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:60817:38"/>and Aſcenſion into Heaven.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> I would learn of you a brief ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of this Matter; and firſt, <hi>What is the relation you have concerning the Birth of Jeſus?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is this: When <hi>Herod</hi> was King of <hi>Judea,</hi> and <hi>Caeſar Auguſtus</hi> was Emperor of the World, then Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus was born at <hi>Bethlehem</hi> in <hi>Judea,</hi> of a Virgin named <hi>Mary,</hi> who conceived him in her Womb, by the Holy Ghoſt, and Power of the Higheſt coming up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on her, and over-ſhadowing her for that end and purpoſe.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the relation you have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Life of Jeſus?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is this: That Jeſus when he had lived about thirty Years a private Life with his Mother <hi>Mary,</hi> and <hi>Joſeph</hi> her Huſband; and when <hi>John the Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tist,</hi> the Son of <hi>Zacharias</hi> the Prieſt, had, by preaching the Baptiſm of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, prepared the way before him, <hi>Jeſus,</hi> I ſay, then came into the World, to bear witneſs to the Truth, and in this exerciſe continued about
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:60817:38"/>three Years, confirming his Teſtimony by Signs and Miracles.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the relation you have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Death of Jeſus?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 'Tis this: That <hi>Jeſus</hi> when he had finiſhed the Work the Father gave him to do, was by wicked Men put to Death, and Crucified.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the relation you have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Reſurrection of Jeſus from the Dead?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 'Tis this: That Jeſus who died and was buried, roſe again the third day from the Dead.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the relation you have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Aſcenſion of Jeſus into Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is this: That Jeſus after his Reſurrection, when he had ſhewed himſelf alive to his Apoſtles (and others) by many infallible Proofs, and was ſeen of them forty days, did in their ſight aſcend into Heaven.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Now to return; <hi>How did God cauſe Jeſus to become the Christ?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> God did cauſe Jeſus to become
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:60817:39"/>the Chriſt, by chooſing him, and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling him to be the Chriſt. <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.18. with <hi>Iſa.</hi> 42.1. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.4. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 42.6. and 49.1. <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.4, 10.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is it for Jeſus to be the Chriſt?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Jeſus is the Chriſt, That is, God's anointed Prophet, Prieſt, and King, by whom alone, and by whom always unto the end of the World, God will rule over all.</p>
               <p>[The Name <hi>Jeſus</hi> ſignifies a Saviour, <hi>Mat.</hi> 1.21. And the <hi>Chriſt,</hi> or <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> or <hi>Meſſias,</hi> (which in the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Language are the ſame that Chriſt is in the <hi>Greek,</hi> and are ſometimes uſed in our Tranſlation, as in <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.25, 26. <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.41. &amp; 4.24.) is in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh, The Anointed.</hi> We read in <hi>John</hi> 1.41. thus in the Line, <hi>We have found the Meſſias, which is, being interpreted, the Chriſt;</hi> but in the Margin, <hi>The Anointed.</hi> It is to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved that theſe terms, <hi>Meſſias</hi> and <hi>Chriſt,</hi> are in the Scriptures applied to Jeſus two manner of ways. For ſometimes they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>note his Perſon; for as <hi>Jeſus</hi> is his Name, ſo alſo <hi>Chriſt</hi> is uſed for his Name, <hi>Matth.</hi> 1.16, 17. So <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> Dan. 9.26. He is called in the Scriptures, not only <hi>Jeſus,</hi> and <hi>Chriſt,</hi> but alſo <hi>Jeſus Chriſt, Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> the <hi>Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:60817:39"/>
               <p>But ſometimes theſe terms, <hi>Chriſt</hi> and <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> or <hi>Meſſias,</hi> denote his Office, as <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.41. &amp; 4.26. In <hi>Act.</hi> 18.28. <hi>For he</hi> [Paul] <hi>mightily convinced the Jews, and that publickly, ſhewing by the Scriptures, that Jeſus was Chriſt.</hi> And thus it is to be taken in the preſent Queſtion and Anſwer. This Jeſus, the Chriſt, is called the <hi>Lord's Chriſt,</hi> Luk. 2.26. Act. 4.26. Rev. 11.15. and <hi>God's Chriſt,</hi> or <hi>the Chriſt of God,</hi> Luk. 9.20. Rev. 12.10. becauſe he was one ſo greatly loved of God, that God appointed and furniſhed him to be a Prophet, Prieſt, and King, whereunto he was of God raiſed and anoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, <hi>Act.</hi> 3.22. <hi>Luk.</hi> 4.18. <hi>Act.</hi> 10.28. <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.15. <hi>Act.</hi> 2.30. <hi>Jer.</hi> 30.9. There never was, or will be, any ſuch Anointed one as he. He had no Predeceſſor, and ſhall have no Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor. Of theſe things, ſee what follows in this Diſcourſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:60817:40"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VI. </hi>Of God's Work of Government in rul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing amongst Men by Jeſus Christ un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the end of the World; and in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, of his Work for the ſaving of Men by Jeſus Chriſt, according to the New Covenant Promiſe, which here is diſcourſed of.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> YOu ſaid, That in God's Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, ſince the raiſing up of Chriſt, you were taught chiefly to mind; Firſt, The Work of God in raiſing up of Chriſt, of which we have now diſcourſed. Secondly, The Work of God in ruling among Men by Jeſus Chriſt unto the end of the World, concerning which we are now to diſcourſe: Tell me therefore, <hi>What you mean by this Work of God?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> This Work of God, in ruling among Men by Jeſus Chriſt, unto the end of the World, does eſpecially conſiſt; 1. In his Work for ſaving of Men by Jeſus Chriſt. 2. In his Work
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:60817:40"/>of judging the World by Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What mean you by that Work of God which is for the ſaving of Men by Jeſus Chriſt?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> I mean that Work of God, and that Work of Jeſus the Chriſt of God, that Men may be ſaved, or be parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of the Promiſe of God in Chriſt by the Goſpel.</p>
               <p>[Joh. 3.17. <hi>God ſent not his Son into the World to condemn the World, but that the World through him might be ſaved.</hi> Joh. 12.47. <hi>I came not</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>to judg</hi> [condemn] <hi>the World, but to ſave the World.</hi> That which God and Chriſt do for the Salvation of Men, is often in the Scriptures (as here af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards will appear) called the Work of God, and of Chriſt. This Work is, That Men may be partakers of the Promiſe of God in Chriſt by the Goſpel. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3.6. <hi>That the Gentiles ſhould be fellow-Heirs, and of the ſame Body, and partakers of his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe in Chriſt by the Goſpel.</hi> That is, That the Gentiles may participate in the Promiſe of God with the Jews as Co-heirs; that is, by a common right, and as being of the ſame Body, that is, by equal right with them, and this by Chriſt, on the terms and conditions
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:60817:41"/>which the Goſpel makes known and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth.]</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> It will be convenient that firſt we diſcourſe of the End and Intent of the Work of God and Chriſt, and then of the Work it ſelf: Wherefore I ſhall ask you a few Queſtions concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Intent of this Work, and in the firſt place this: <hi>What are we to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand here by the Promiſe of God?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> By the Promiſe of God we are here to underſtand that Promiſe, whereby God, according to his pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, hath promiſed to give Eternal Life, in or by Jeſus Chriſt, unto all that believe in him, thorow his Son Jeſus Chriſt, that they may be to the praiſe of his Glory.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> For the ſetting forth of this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe more diſtinctly, I ſhall query con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the ſeveral parts of your An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer; as firſt, <hi>What is that eternal Life which God hath promiſed?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> That Eternal Life which God hath promiſed, is that Salvation which is in Chriſt Jeſus with Eternal Glory.</p>
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:60817:41"/>
               <p>[John 2.25. <hi>And this is the Promiſe that he hath promiſed us, even Eternal Life.</hi> This Matter of the Promiſe is often called <hi>Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal</hi> or <hi>Everlaſting Life,</hi> alſo <hi>Life.</hi> Now this Eternal Life doth conſiſt in that Salvation that is in Chriſt Jeſus, and alſo in Eternal Glory, as we learn from 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.10.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>But what is the Salvation that is in Chriſt Jeſus?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Salvation that is in Chriſt Jeſus, is a deliverance from the Wrath to come, 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1.10.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>And what is this Eternal Glory?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> This Eternal Glory, is a like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to God, by ſeeing him as he is, 1 Joh. 3.2.</p>
               <p>[Theſe two, <hi>Salvation</hi> and <hi>Eternal Glory,</hi> are in the Scriptures ſometimes noted by one of theſe names; as, by Salvation, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.5. and elſe-where. Alſo by Eternal Glory, as 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.10. and Glory, as <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.23. The Glory of God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.2. and the like.]</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> You ſaid, That God hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to give Eternal Life in or by Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>What mean you by this?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> God giveth Eternal Life in or by Jeſus, in that Jeſus Chriſt is the
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:60817:42"/>Mediator between God and Men, in God's giving of Eternal Life unto them.</p>
               <p>[Rom. 6.23. <hi>Eternal Life is the Gift of God through</hi> [in or by] <hi>Jeſus Chriſt our Lord.</hi> 1 Joh. 5.11. <hi>This is the Record, That God hath given us Eternal Life, and this Life is in his Son.</hi> 1 Tim. 2.4, 5, &amp;c. <hi>Who</hi> (to wit, God our Saviour) <hi>will have all Men to be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and to come to the knowledg</hi> [acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment] <hi>of the Truth: For there is one God, and one Mediator between God and Men, the Man Chriſt Jeſus, who gave himſelf a Ranſom for all,</hi> &amp;c. Joh. 14.6. <hi>Jeſus faith unto him, I am the Way, and the Truth, and the Life; no Man cometh unto the Father but by me.]</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> You ſaid, That God hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to give Eternal Life to all that believe in him through Jeſus Chriſt: <hi>But who are they?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> They that believe in God through Jeſus Chriſt are they, who ſo believe the Promiſe of God, as to hope in God, and live to him thorow Jeſus Chriſt, and that to the end.</p>
               <p>[1 Pet. 1.20, 21. <hi>Who</hi> [which Chriſt] <hi>ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily was fore-ordained before the foundation of
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:60817:42"/>the World, but was manifeſt in theſe laſt times for you, who by</hi> [thorow] <hi>him</hi> [Chriſt] <hi>do believe in God that raiſed him up from the Dead, and gave him Glory, that your Faith and Hope might be in God.</hi> Theſe Perſons in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures are ſet forth, ſometimes only by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving, as <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.22. <hi>The Scripture hath con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded all under Sin, that the Promiſe by Faith of Jeſus Chriſt might be given to them that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve.</hi> Sometimes by believing in the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as in <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.24. <hi>Verily, verily, I ſay unto you, He that heareth my Word, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieveth on him that ſent me, hath everlaſting Life, and ſhall not come into condemnation, but is paſſed from Death unto Life.</hi> Sometimes by believing in Chriſt, as in <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.47. <hi>Verily, verily I ſay unto you, He that believeth on me bath Everlaſting Life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe, and many the like Expreſſions of the ſame ſignification, we meet with in the Holy Scripture. Now we are to underſtand, that whereſoever Eternal Life, in the poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of it, is promiſed to Believing, there ſuch a Believing is intended that the Goſpel requires, which is an hoping in God, and living to him through Jeſus Chriſt, and that to the end: For meer Belief is not ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent; <hi>Jam.</hi> 2.14, &amp;c. <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.23. &amp; 8.30. &amp; 12.42. Nor is any Faith ſufficient that laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not to the end, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.38, &amp;c.</p>
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:60817:43"/>
               <p>Q. <hi>But what is it to hope in God thorow Jeſus Chriſt?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To hope in God thorow Jeſus Chriſt, is to hope or truſt unto the end, both in God and Chriſt for Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Life, as the Gift of God thorow Jeſus Chriſt our Lord, and is ſuch a hope, that is laid up in Heaven, and as ſuch a Grace that is to be brought unto us at the Revelation of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>[<hi>We are ſaved by Hope,</hi> Rom. 8.24. <hi>This Hope muſt be an Hope in God,</hi> 1 Pet. 1.21. Act. 24.15. 1 Tim. 4.10. &amp; 6.17. And <hi>in Chriſt,</hi> 1 Cor. 15.19. 1 Theſſ. 1.3. 1 Tim. 1.1. Rom. 15.12. Epheſ. 1.12, 13. That which by this Hope is to be looked for and expected, is eternal Life, <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.2. &amp; 3.7. which eternal Life is the Gift of God thorow Jeſus Chriſt our Lord, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.22. and of all Gifts the beſt; for it is the Hope, or Good hoped for, which is laid up in Heaven, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.6. and the bleſſed, or happy, that is happy making Hope, <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.13. and the laſt Gift, being the Gift which is to be brought at the Revelation [or coming] of Jeſus Chriſt, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.13. It is alſo called <hi>Grace,</hi> becauſe a Gift that proceeds from the Grace of God,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:60817:43"/>and of Jeſus Chriſt, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.13. 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1.11, 12. Hence it appears that this future Good, muſt be ſought chiefly and humbly; and that all which is neceſſary for obtaining it, muſt alſo be hoped for from God thorow Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.33. <hi>Luk.</hi> 17.10. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.5. <hi>Joh.</hi> 16.23, 24.</p>
               <p>And thus we muſt hope to the end, or conſtantly, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.13. <hi>Col.</hi> 1.23. <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.6.]</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>And what is it to live to God tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row Jeſus Chriſt?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To live to God thorow Jeſus Chriſt, is, To live to God and Chriſt, in ſerving the God and Father of Jeſus Chriſt, in Holineſs and Righteouſneſs before him, all the days of our Life; and in ſerving Jeſus Chriſt, as Lord of all, and as the Head and Huſand of Believers, who are his Church and Body.</p>
               <p>[Rom. 6.11. <hi>Likewiſe reckon ye alſo your ſelves to be dead indeed unto Sin, but alive</hi> [living] <hi>unto God, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord.</hi> Gal. 2.19. <hi>For I through the Law am dead to the Law, that I might live unto God.</hi> 2 Cor. 5.15. <hi>And that he died for all, that they which live, ſhould not henceforth live unto themſelves, but unto him which died for them,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:60817:44"/>and roſe again.</hi> 1 Theſſ. 1.9. <hi>Ye turned to God from Idols, to ſerve the living and true God,</hi> &amp;c. Luk. 1.74, 75. <hi>That he</hi> [the Lord God of Iſrael] <hi>would grant unto us, that we being delivered out of the hands of our Enemies, might ſerve him without fear, in Holineſs and Righteouſneſs before him, all the days of our Life. See</hi> Mat. 4.10. Rom. 1.9. 2 Tim. 1.3. Heb. 9.14. <hi>&amp;</hi> 12.28. Rom. 14.18. <hi>For he that in theſe things</hi> [Righteouſneſs, Peace, and Joy in the Holy Ghoſt] <hi>ſerveth Chriſt, is acceptable to God, and approved of Men. See</hi> Joh. 12.26. Rom. 16.18. Rev. 1.1. <hi>In</hi> Eph. 5.22, &amp;c. <hi>Wives ſubmit your ſelves unto your own Husbands as unto the Lord: for the Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band is the Head of the Wiſe, even as Chriſt is the Head of the Church, and he is the Saviour of the Body. Therefore as the Church is ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject unto Chriſt; ſo let the Wives be unto their own Husbands in every thing.</hi> To ſerve God and Chriſt, is from Love to obey them, as having reſpect to the Authority of both, and aiming at the Glory of both. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.2. and <hi>v.</hi> 14. <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.9. <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.27. <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.18, &amp;c. <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.27. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3.21. <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.11. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.31. <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.6. 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1.12. Thus to live, is to live, <hi>not to the Luſts of Men, but to the Will of God,</hi> 1 Pet. 4.2.]</p>
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:60817:44"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> You ſaid, That God according to his purpoſe did thus promiſe, <hi>What mean you thereby?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> I mean, That God having through his Grace ſo purpoſed before the World began, did at length bring to light this purpoſe of his, and that by Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>[<hi>Tit.</hi> 1.1, 2, 3. Paul <hi>a Servant of God, and an Apoſtle of Jeſus Chriſt, according to the Faith of God's Elect, and the acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Truth, which is after Godlineſs, in hope of eternal Life, which God, that cannot lie, promiſed</hi> [in purpoſe] <hi>before the World began: But hath in due time manifeſted his Word</hi> [Promiſe] <hi>through preaching</hi> [the publication of his purpoſe] <hi>which is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted unto me,</hi> &amp;c. 2 Tim. 1.9, 10. <hi>Who hath ſaved us, and called us with an Holy Calling, not according to our Works, but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his own Purpoſe and Grace,</hi> [graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Purpoſe] <hi>which was given us in Chriſt Jeſus before the World began; but is now made manifeſt by the appearing of our Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, who hath aboliſhed Death, and hath brought Life and Immortality</hi> [an Immortal Life] <hi>to Light through the Goſpel.</hi>]</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> You ſaid, That God hath thus
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:60817:45"/>promiſed to Believers, that they might be to the praiſe of his Glory: <hi>What is your meaning here?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> I mean this, That God in thus promiſing had for his principal end therein, that the Glory of his Grace, Wiſdom, and Power, might be ſhewen forth on Believers, and praiſed by them. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.12. &amp; 2.7.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Now tell me, <hi>What is it for Men to be partakers of this Promiſe of God?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Men are then ſaid to be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of this Promiſe, when they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Heirs of Eternal Life, and do at length poſſeſs it. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.29. <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.7. <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.17. <hi>Jam.</hi> 2.5. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.7. <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.14. &amp; 10.36.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is it to be partakers of this Promiſe by the Goſpel?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Men are ſaid to be Partakers of the Promiſe by the Goſpel, Becauſe Faith cometh by the Goſpel, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Goſpel is the Power of God unto Salvation to every one that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieveth. <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.17. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.13. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.16.</p>
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:60817:45"/>
               <p>Q. <hi>But what do you mean by the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Goſpel is that Revelation of the Myſtery concerning the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of Eternal Life, which began to be ſpoken by the Lord Jeſus.</p>
               <p>[The word <hi>Goſpel</hi> is uſed to expreſs a word in Greek, which in general denotes any good and joyful Meſſage, or good and glad Tydings; and which in ſpecial, and by way of eminency, ſignifies that good and glad Tydings brought into the World by Jeſus Chriſt: in which ſenſe ſome would rather uſe the term <hi>Evangelie,</hi> than Goſpel, following therein moſt Nations, who retain in this ſenſe the Greek word, and that not unadviſedly.</p>
               <p>That we call the Goſpel, is that Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or diſcovery of the Myſtery concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Promiſe of Eternal Life, which firſt began to be ſpoken by Jeſus Chriſt. See <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.25. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3.3, &amp;c. <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.17. <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.3. It is called the Revelation of the Myſtery concerning this Promiſe, becauſe this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe was before the coming of Chriſt, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in a Myſtery, that is, in Types and Figures, after an obſcure way and manner. But Chriſt hath expounded this Promiſe, making known the ſubſtance of the ſhadow,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:60817:46"/>and bringing forth clearly the Spirit [that is, the meaning] of the Letter. <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.13, &amp;c. and 9.8, 9. <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.13. <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.17. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.6. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.10.]</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Before we return, I have one Queſtion yet to ask you; namely, <hi>Whether nothing elſe but Eternal Life is in this Promiſe promiſed to Believers?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> In the Promiſe of Eternal Life, all good things that muſt come from God, and are neceſſary for obtaining it, are neceſſarily included in this <hi>Promiſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>[1 Tim. 4.8. <hi>Godlineſs is profitable unto all things, having the Promiſe of the Life that now is, and of that which is to come.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Touching the matter of this Anſwer, ſee in that which follows.]</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VII. </hi>Of God's Work by Jeſus Chriſt, for the ſaving of Sinners.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> YOu having thus ſpoken of the Promiſe of Eternal Life, which is the Promiſe of the New Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, let us conſider the Work of
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:60817:46"/>God for the ſaving of Men by Jeſus Chriſt, which you ſaid is that Work of God, and that Work of Jeſus, the Chriſt of God, that Men may be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved: <hi>What have you learned in the general concerning this Work?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Concerning God's Work for the ſaving of Men (or preparing them for Salvation) by Jeſus Chriſt, I have learned, that this Work doth reſpect, firſt, Thoſe that are the Servants of Sin, and the Children of the Devil. Secondly, Thoſe that are the Servants of Obedience, &amp; the Children of God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> It being ſo, we will ſpeak of this Work accordingly, beginning with that part which reſpecteth the former ſort of Perſons you mentioned: But becauſe it will be needful to know who they are, I therefore ask you, <hi>Who are they that are the Servants of Sin, and Children of the Devil?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> All they who live in Sin, which is the tranſgreſſion of the Law of God, are the Servants of Sin, and Children of the Devil.</p>
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:60817:47"/>
               <p>[The Law of God is a binding directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from God concerning Duty, forbidding that which is Evil, and commanding that which is needful to be done. Now the Tranſgreſſion of this Law, either in doing what it forbids, or leaving undone what it commands, is ſin, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.4. &amp; 5.17. That man, whoever he be, that lives in Sin, or commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth Sin, by loving Sin, and walking in it, is a Servant of Sin, and a Child of the Devil. Joh. 8.34. <hi>Verily, verily, I ſay unto you,</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>Whoſoever committeth Sin, is the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant of Sin.</hi> Rom. 6.2. Such are ſaid to live in Sin. 1 John 3.10. <hi>In this the Children of God are manifeſt, and the Children of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil: Whoſoever doth not Righteouſneſs is not of God, neither he that loveth not his Brother.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>But why are they that live in Sin thus called?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> They that live in Sin are called <hi>the Servants of Sin,</hi> becauſe they yield their Members Servants to unclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and to iniquity unto iniquity, and may expect the Wages of Sin, which is Death; and they are called <hi>the Children of the Devil,</hi> becauſe they do the Works of the Devil, and may expect to go into everlaſting Fire with
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:60817:47"/>the Devil &amp; his Angels. [<hi>Rom.</hi> 6.16, 19, 21, 23. <hi>Joh.</hi> 8.41, 44. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.8. <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.41.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Now tell me, <hi>What is the Work of God by Jeſus Chriſt for the ſaving of Sinners?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Work of God by Jeſus Chriſt for the ſaving of Sinners, does reſpect their Repentance, and upon Repentance the forgiveneſs of their Sins, and their becoming the Children of God.</p>
               <p>[This Work does reſpect the change of their Hearts by Repentance, whereby of evil Men they become good, like unto good Trees, which are fit to bring forth good Fruit, <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.33. This Work alſo reſpects the change of their State, in that by Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance they obtain that Juſtification and Adoption, which are here attainable. Of theſe things ſee afterwards.]</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> It will be convenient to inquire after the Deſign of this Work, before we ſpeak of the Work it ſelf; and therefore I ſhall firſt ask you this Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion; <hi>What is Repentance?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> This Repentance we are ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of, Is a turning to God with the
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:60817:48"/>whole Heart, in order to the ſerving of him all the days of our Life.</p>
               <p>[<hi>Repentance</hi> is declared to be a turning to God, and as that which foregoes our living in his Service. Act. 26.20. <hi>I</hi> [Paul] <hi>ſhewed firſt to them of</hi> Damaſcus, <hi>and at</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>and throughout all the Coaſts of</hi> Judea, <hi>and then to the Gentiles, that they ſhould repent and turn to God, and do Works meet for Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</hi> 1 Theſſ. 1.9. <hi>Ye turned to God from Idols, to ſerve the living and true God, and to wait for his Son from Heaven,</hi> &amp;c. See <hi>Acts</hi> 15.19. This turning muſt be with the whole Heart. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.3. <hi>Joel</hi> 2.12.]</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>But wherein does this turning to God with the whole Heart conſist?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Turning to God with the whole Heart, does conſiſt in that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of the Heart, whereby a Man, from a due apprehenſion of his Sins and Danger, alſo of God's Will and Promiſe, and from a due conſideration thereof, does ſuitably thereunto con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs or acknowledg his Sins unto God, and purpoſe or reſolve to ſerve God, and keep his Commandments.</p>
               <p>[This turning to G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d, or this Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, does lie in a confeſſion of Sin, and
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:60817:48"/>in a reſolution of ſerving God, that is, of forſaking Sin. The Parable of the Prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal, in <hi>Luke</hi> 15.17, &amp;c. ſpeaks forth this. Add <hi>Prov.</hi> 28.13. <hi>He that covereth his Sins ſhall not proſper, but whoſo confeſſeth and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaketh them ſhall have Mercy.</hi> See <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 14.1, 2, 3. Sometimes the whole is ſet forth by one of theſe. Thus it is by this confeſſion and acknowledgment of ſins, 1 <hi>John</hi> 1.9. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 32.5. &amp; 5.3. <hi>Jer.</hi> 3.13. Thus alſo by this reſolution of ſerving God. <hi>Jer.</hi> 5.24. &amp; 30.21. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 11.16.</p>
               <p>This Repentance, or turning to God, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſeth from that apprehenſion and conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration mentioned. See for this <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.23. 1 <hi>King.</hi> 8.37, 38. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18 32. <hi>Matth.</hi> 13.15. <hi>Act.</hi> 11.21. 1 <hi>King.</hi> 8.47. <hi>Luk.</hi> 15.17. <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.29. <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 50.22. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 12.3. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 7.2. <hi>Hag.</hi> 1.5, 7. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18.14, 28. <hi>Prov.</hi> 2.5.]</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>When is Confeſſion in Repentance ſuch as it ought to be?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> This Confeſſion is then ſuch as it ought to be, when in confeſſing we are humbled, abhorring and condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning our ſelves for our Sins, with ſhame and ſorrow; and when we make ſupplication to God with earneſtneſs and hope for Pardon and Acceptance.</p>
               <pb n="92" facs="tcp:60817:49"/>
               <p>[This Confeſſion muſt be with humilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and ſupplication. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 7.14. &amp; 33.12. Repentance is ſometimes ſet forth by Humiliation, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 33.19. <hi>Jam.</hi> 4.10. by a contrite, broken, and humble Heart, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.17. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 57.15.</p>
               <p>This Humiliation is an abhorring of our ſelves, and condemning of our ſelves with ſhame and ſorrow for our Sins. <hi>Job</hi> 42.6. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 20.43. &amp; 36.31. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.31. <hi>Ezra</hi> 9.13. <hi>Luk.</hi> 15.19, 21. <hi>Jer.</hi> 6.15. &amp; 8.12. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.21. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 44.9. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16.61, 63. &amp; 43.10, 11. &amp; 36.32. <hi>Pſalm</hi> 38.18. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.9, 10. <hi>Jam.</hi> 4.9. (<hi>Ezra</hi> 10.6.) <hi>Iſa.</hi> 22.12. <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.4. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 58.5. There muſt alſo be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication to God for Pardon and Accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and it muſt be done with an earneſt deſire and hope to attain the ſame. 1 <hi>King.</hi> 8.47, &amp;c. <hi>Jer.</hi> 14.20, 21. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 5.15. &amp; 14.2. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 11.14. &amp; 33.12. <hi>Act.</hi> 9.11. <hi>Luk.</hi> 15.19. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.12.13. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55.13.]</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>When is Reſolution of Amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſuch as it ought to be?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Reſolution of Amendment, or of ſerving God, is then ſuch as it ought to be, when truſting in God we purpoſe to forſake all Sin, and to obſerve all God's Commandments to
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:60817:49"/>the end of our Lives, and that with the utmoſt of Self-denial, in all worldly Pleaſure, Profit, Honour, and Safety.</p>
               <p>[The Purpoſe of the Heart in Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, muſt be according to the true nature of ſerving God: and therefore ſuch as hath been deſcribed. It muſt be a purpoſe of leaving Sin in the General, and of known Sins in ſpecial, and of doing the Will of God fully. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.1, 2. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 14.3. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.16, &amp;c. And this muſt be a Purpoſe of ſerving God to the end, with the utmoſt of Self-denial. Mat. 16.24. <hi>Then ſaid Jeſus unto his Diſciples, If any Man will come after me, let him deny himſelf, and take up his Croſs and follow me.</hi> Read <hi>Luke</hi> 14.25, to the end of the 33 verſe.</p>
               <p>And Men in this purpoſing, muſt hope and truſt in God for help and aſſiſtance, that they may do according to their Intent and Purpoſe. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 51.5. <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.21. <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.12. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37.3, 5. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 57.13.]</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> You having declar'd what Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance is, I ſhall next enquire con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Privileges which they have that repent, namely, the forgive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of their Sins, and their being the
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:60817:50"/>Children of God: Tell me, <hi>What is this forgiveneſs?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The forgiveneſs of Sin, which they that repent, obtain from God, is that pardon of their Sins, whence they have peace with God, as one who by Promiſe hath delivered them from the Wrath to come. [<hi>Rom.</hi> 5.1. <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.12.]</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>And what is it for theſe repenting Souls to become the Children of God?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> They become the Children of God, in that they come to be as Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to God, having acceſs into a ſtate of Grace or Favour, wherein they may boaſt in hope of the Glory of God. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.2.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>But is Repentance neceſſary and ſufficient for obtaining this good and bleſſed condition?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is ſo, as the Holy Scriptures plentifully teach us. See <hi>Luke</hi> 13.3. <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.5. <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.20, &amp;c. <hi>Act.</hi> 11.18. <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.15. <hi>James</hi> 3.20. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18.30. <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.23.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> If ſo; <hi>How muſt we underſtand thoſe Scriptures which ſhew, that Faith
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:60817:50"/>or Believing is neceſſary and ſufficient for obtaining the fore-mentioned Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits.</hi> See <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.1, 2. <hi>Act.</hi> 13.39. and elſewhere.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> In ſuch Scriptures where only Faith, or only Repentance is menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned, there Faith and Repentance are the ſame: for there Repentance is implied in Faith, or Faith in Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</p>
               <p>[Theſe words, <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Repentance,</hi> or <hi>Believing</hi> and <hi>Repenting</hi> in the buſineſs of our Salvation, are uſed in the Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, either alone or together. When a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, they ſignity one and the ſame thing; but when together, as in <hi>Act.</hi> 20.21. <hi>Mark</hi> 1.15. Then Repentance hath reſpect only to our Works, and Faith hath reſpect only to our Hope.</p>
               <p>It will moreover be for much advantage to know and obſerve concerning the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned terms, theſe two things among others.</p>
               <p>Firſt, That thoſe Terms, as above-uſed, do ſometimes only ſight, That which God requires for our admittance into a ſtate of Grace. Thus the word <hi>Faith,</hi> and <hi>to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve,</hi> is uſed, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.1, 2. <hi>Act.</hi> 15.9. <hi>Rom.</hi>
                  <pb n="96" facs="tcp:60817:51"/>10.10. And ſo the word <hi>Repentance,</hi> and <hi>to repent,</hi> Mat. 3.8. Act. 26.20. Mat. 11.20. So alſo <hi>Repentance,</hi> and <hi>Faith,</hi> or, <hi>The Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of Repentance and Faith,</hi> Heb. 6.1.</p>
               <p>Secondly, That the ſame terms uſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone or together, do oft-times ſignify the whole that God requires for our admittance into a ſtate of Glory. Thus the words <hi>Faith,</hi> and <hi>to believe,</hi> are uſed, <hi>Acts</hi> 26.18. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.9. <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.16. <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.11. Thus al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo <hi>Repentance,</hi> and <hi>to repent,</hi> are uſed, <hi>Luke</hi> 24.47. <hi>Act.</hi> 5.31. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.9. <hi>Mat.</hi> 4.17. <hi>Act.</hi> 17.30. And ſo alſo theſe terms <hi>Repentance</hi> and <hi>Faith,</hi> alſo <hi>to repent,</hi> and <hi>to believe,</hi> when conjoyn'd, <hi>Act.</hi> 20.21. <hi>Mar.</hi> 1.15.]</p>
               <p>Q. Now let us return to conſider the Work of God by Chriſt Jeſus for the faving of Sinners. <hi>What have you learned concerning this Work?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Concerning the Work of God by Jeſus Chriſt for the ſaving of Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, I have learned that it conſiſteth in God's making by Jeſus Chriſt a way for Sinners to come to Repentance, and thereby to the forgiveneſs of their Sins, and acceptance with him, and in calling them to Repentance by Jeſus Chriſt, for the pardon of their Sins,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:60817:51"/>and acceptance with him. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.18, 19. <hi>Luk.</hi> 1.79.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How has God made by Jeſus Chriſt this way for Sinners?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> God hath made this way for Sinners; firſt, By the Death of his Son, who by his Death is made a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitiation for the Sins of the World, and has open'd a way for the coming of the Word of Reconciliation to them. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.8, 10. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.13, &amp;c. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.10. &amp; 2.2. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.13. <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.28.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Wherein does the Work of God appear in the Death of Chriſt for the ſaving of Sinners?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Work of God appears in the Death of Chriſt for the ſaving of Sinners, in that for this end and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe God willed that Chriſt ſhould be obedient unto Death, even the Death of the Croſs, and in that he helped him therein. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.5, &amp;c. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 40.6. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49.8. &amp; 50.5, &amp;c. <hi>Act.</hi> 2.25. <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.7.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Wherein does the Work of Chriſt appear in his own Death for the ſaving of Sinners?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="98" facs="tcp:60817:52"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It appears in that he firſt wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to be thus obedient, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards became obedient unto Death, even the Death of the Croſs, that Sinners might be ſaved. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.5, &amp;c. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 40.6, &amp;c. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 50.5, &amp;c. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.6. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.8.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> You having ſhew'd, that God by the Death of Chriſt hath made a way for the ſaving of Sinners, <hi>Now tell me how elſe God has done it?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> God has made for Sinners a way to Repentance and Forgiveneſs, not only by the Death of Chriſt, but alſo by the ſitting down of Chriſt at the right Hand of God, in which eſtate he hath power to give Repentance, and the forgiveneſs of Sins. <hi>Act.</hi> 5.30, 31.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Wherein does the Work of God for the ſaving of Sinners, appear in Chriſt's ſitting at his right hand?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It appears in that God raiſed him from the Dead, took him up into Heaven, and ſet him at his right Hand. <hi>Act.</hi> 2.24, 32. <hi>Mark</hi> 16.19. <hi>Luk.</hi> 24.51. <hi>Act.</hi> 1.9. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.20.</p>
               <pb n="99" facs="tcp:60817:52"/>
               <p>Q. <hi>Wherein does the Work of Chriſt appear in his ſitting at God's right Hand?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It appears in that he obtained this eſtate by being obedient unto the Death, even the Death of the Croſs. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.8, 9.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> You having declar'd the Work of God by Jeſus Chriſt for the ſaving of Sinners, by making a way for them to Repentance and Pardon, it remains that we ſpeak of God's Work for the ſaving of Sinners, by the calling them to Repentance. <hi>What have you learnt concerning this?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Concerning God's calling of Sinners by Jeſus Chriſt unto Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, I have learned, That God by Jeſus Chriſt through the Goſpel, does command Sinners to repent, and does promiſe upon Repentance the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveneſs of their Sins: and that God and Chriſt thus call them with pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and long-ſuffering. <hi>Act.</hi> 2.38, 39. &amp; 3.26. &amp; 17.30. 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.14. <hi>Act.</hi> 10.43. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.9. <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.21. <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.22. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.16.</p>
               <pb n="100" facs="tcp:60817:53"/>
               <p>Q. <hi>How may God be ſaid to call Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners by Jeſus Chriſt unto Repentance?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> God may be ſaid ſo to do, in that he ſent Jeſus Chriſt to call Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners to Repentance. <hi>Act.</hi> 3.26.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How may Jeſus Chriſt be ſaid to call Sinners to Repentance?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Jeſus Chriſt may be ſaid to call Sinners to Repentance, in that he comes in the Name of God, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands Sinners to Repent, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeth Pardon to them upon their Repentance. <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.43. &amp; 10.25.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>When did Chriſt come and call Sinners to Repentance?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Chriſt did firſt, in the days of his Fleſh, call Sinners to Repentance, and that in his own Perſon, and by his Diſciples. <hi>Mat.</hi> 4.19. &amp; 9.13. <hi>Mark</hi> 6.12.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>When elſe did Chriſt come and call to Repentance?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Chriſt after his Reſurrection from the dead, came and called Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners to Repentance. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.17. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.19.</p>
               <pb n="101" facs="tcp:60817:53"/>
               <p>Q. <hi>How did Chriſt after his Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection come and call Sinners to Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Chriſt came and called by his Apoſtles and others, who in Chriſt's ſtead do teach and intreat Sinners to be reconciled unto God. <hi>Act.</hi> 13.46, 47. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.20. <hi>Luk.</hi> 24.46, 47.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How may theſe be ſaid to be in Chriſt's ſtead in their preaching the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Theſe may be ſaid to be in Chriſt's ſtead; firſt, in that they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive their Commiſſion from Jeſus Chriſt to preach the Goſpel. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.17. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.11, 12.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the Commiſſion Christ gave to his Apoſtles, after his Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from the Dead?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is this: <hi>All Power is given unto me in Heaven and in Earth: Go ye therefore, and teach all Nations, bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizing them in</hi> [into] <hi>the Name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Ghoſt: and lo, I am with you al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, even unto the end of the World.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:60817:54"/>
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.18, 19, 20.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How elſe are they in Chriſt's ſtead in preaching the Goſpel?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Upon this account alſo they are ſuch, Becauſe Chriſt who enables them for the Work, hath appointed them to be his Miniſters, and in his Name to preach the Goſpel. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.12. <hi>Luk.</hi> 24.47. <hi>Act.</hi> 4.12. &amp; 9.27. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.5. <hi>Act.</hi> 26.15, &amp;c. <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.16. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.6. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.1.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Are none but Miniſters to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour the ſaving of Sinners, by bringing them to Repentance?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> All Chriſtians are to endeavour, by their Words and Works, to ſave Sinners, by bringing them to Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.15, 16. <hi>James</hi> 5.20. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.16. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.1.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:60817:54"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VIII. </hi>Of God's Work by Jeſus Chriſt for the ſaving of Converts.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> SEing we have ſpoken of God's Work for the ſaving of Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, let us now ſpeak of that which is for the ſaving of Converts, who by Repentance have their Sins forgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and are become the Children of God. <hi>What is God's Work by Jeſus Christ for the ſaving of theſe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Work of God by Jeſus Chriſt for the ſaving of his Children, is that whereby God bringeth them unto Glory by Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>[Heb. 2.10. <hi>For it became him</hi> [God] <hi>for whom are all things, and by whom are all things, in bringing many Sons unto Glory, to make the Captain of their Salvation perfect through Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings.</hi>]</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Wherein does this Work conſist?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> God's Work by Jeſus Chriſt, of bringing his Children unto Glory, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth in preparing them for Glory, and
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:60817:55"/>poſſeſſing them with it. <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.23.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How does God by Jeſus Chriſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare them for Glory?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> God does this, by creating them in Chriſt Jeſus unto good Works, and by confirming them therein unto the end.</p>
               <p>[Epheſ. 2.10. <hi>We are God's Workmanſhip, created in Chriſt Jeſus unto good Works, which God hath before ordained, that we ſhould walk in them.</hi> 1 Cor. 1.8, 9. <hi>Who</hi> [God] <hi>ſhall alſo confirm you unto the end, that ye may be blameleſs in the day of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt. God is faithful by whom ye were called unto the fellowſhip of his Son Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> 1 Theſ. 5.23, 24. <hi>And the very God of Peace ſanctify you wholly: And I pray God your whole Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and Soul, and Body, be preſerved blame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs unto the coming of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt. Faithful is be that calleth you, who alſo will do it.</hi> Heb. 13.20, 21. <hi>Now the God of Peace, that brought again from the dead our Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, that great Shepherd of the Sheep, through the Blood of the Everlaſting Covenant, make you perfect in every good Work to do his Will, working in you that which is well-pleaſing in his ſight, through Jeſus Chriſt, to whom be Glory, for ever and ever.</hi> Amen.]</p>
               <pb n="105" facs="tcp:60817:55"/>
               <p>Q. <hi>But how does God thus ſanctify Believers?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> God does this by his Spirit, which he gives to Believers, and by which he works in them for their Sanctification, and all this thorow Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>[1 Pet. 1.2. <hi>Elect according to the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg of God the Father, thorow ſanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Spirit, unto Obedience, and ſprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of the Blood of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> Epheſ. 1.13. <hi>In whom</hi> [which Chriſt] <hi>alſo after that ye believed, ye were ſealed with that Holy Spirit of Promiſe.</hi> Tit. 3.5, &amp;c. <hi>God our Saviour ſaved us by the waſhing of Regeneration, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newing of the Holy Ghoſt, which he ſhed on us abundantly through Jeſus Chriſt our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>See</hi> Joh. 3.5. Ezek. 36.25, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>]</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is that which God worketh in Believers by his Spirit, that they may be confirmed unto the end?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> God by his Spirit does enligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten them concerning his Will, and does ſtrengthen them that they may walk worthy of the Lord unto all pleaſing, in all patience and long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuffering with joyfulneſs. [<hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.17,
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:60817:56"/>18. &amp; 3.14, &amp;c. <hi>Col.</hi> 1.9, 10, 11.]</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Is there nothing by which God and Christ do through the Spirit ſanctify Believers?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Yes; for the Word of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel is us'd for their Sanctification, and ſometimes Chaſtiſement.</p>
               <p>[For <hi>the Word of the Goſpel,</hi> ſee <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.16. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.26. For <hi>Chaſtiſement,</hi> ſee <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.5, &amp;c. <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.19.]</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Is there nothing that God by Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Christ worketh out of Believers for their Sanctification?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Yes; And among other things, <hi>God will not ſuffer them to be tempted above that they are able, but will with the Temptation alſo make a way to eſcape, that they may be able to bear it.</hi> 1 Cor. 10.13.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What in this Work of Sanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is peculiar to Christ?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> He gave himſelf for the Church, that he might ſanctify and cleanſe it with the waſhing of Water by the Word. And he ever liveth to make interceſſion for us. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.25, 26. <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.25.</p>
               <pb n="107" facs="tcp:60817:56"/>
               <p>Q. <hi>What muſt Believers do that they may be Holy, and confirmed unto the end?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> They muſt cleanſe themſelves from all filthineſs of Fleſh and Spirit, perfecting Holineſs in the Fear of God. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.1.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Can you ſet forth this more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Yes, after this manner; They building up themſelves in their moſt Holy Faith, praying in the Holy Ghoſt, muſt keep themſelves in the Love of God, looking for the Mercy of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt unto Eternal Life. <hi>Jud.</hi> 20, 21.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> I would hear ſomething from you touching the particulars of your Anſwer: Wherefore I ask you in the firſt place this Queſtion; <hi>What is it for Believers to build up themſelves in their moſt Holy Faith?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Believers may be then ſaid to build up themſelves in their moſt Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Faith, when they rightly endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, by the means God vouchſafeth
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:60817:57"/>them, both in private and in publick, to encreaſe in the knowledg and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief of the Doctrine of Chriſt. <hi>Col.</hi> 2.7. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.18. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.7. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.11, &amp;c. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.1, 2.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is it for Believers to pray in the Holy Ghoſt?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Believers may be then ſaid to pray in the Holy Ghoſt, when ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Will of God, made known by the Holy Ghoſt, they make known their Requeſts unto God by Prayer and Supplication, with Thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving, both in private and publick, as they have opportunity. <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.6. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.14. <hi>Matth.</hi> 6.5, &amp;c. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.14, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What general Direction have Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers for Prayer and Thanksgiving?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> That which our Saviour gave to his Apoſtles, in <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.5, &amp;c. add thereto that of our Saviour after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, in <hi>Joh.</hi> 16.23, 24. <hi>Verily, veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, I ſay unto you, Whatſoever ye ſhall ask the Father in my Name, he will give it you. Hitherto have ye asked nothing
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:60817:57"/>in my Name: Ask and ye ſhall receive, that your joy may be full.</hi> Add that of the Apoſtle, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.20. <hi>Give thanks always for all things unto God, and the Father, in the Name of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>But what is it to pray and give thanks in the Name of Jeſus Chriſt?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To pray and give thanks in the Name of Jeſus Chriſt, is to draw nigh to God therein with confidence, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Jeſus Chriſt is our High Prieſt, that maketh interceſſion for us. <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.14, 15, 16. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.5. <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.15.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What have you learnt concerning that Cup of Bleſſing, or Thanksgiving, which the Apoſtle ſpeaketh of in</hi> 1 Cor. 10.16?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> I have learned, That the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle there ſpeaketh of the Lord's Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, which is to be uſed with Thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving in the Churches of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What mean you by the Lord's Supper?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> I mean, A certain uſe of Bread and a Cup, which Chriſt our Lord
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:60817:58"/>hath appointed for a remembrance of him: For as often as we eat this Bread, and drink this Cup, we ſhew the Lord's Death till he come. <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.26, &amp;c. <hi>Mark</hi> 14.22, &amp;c. <hi>Luk.</hi> 22.19, &amp;c. 1 Cor. 11.23, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. Now tell me; <hi>What is it for Believers to keep themſelves in the Love of God?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Believers may be then ſaid to keep themſelves in the Love of God, when they ſo uſe their Knowledg or Belief of the Goſpel, and the Power they have received from God, as to deny Ungodlineſs and worldly Luſts, and to live ſoberly, righteouſly, and godly in this preſent World. <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.11, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is it for Believers to look for the Mercy of our Lord Jeſus Christ unto Eternal Life?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is nothing elſe but to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue to the end, in an expectation of that Reward of ſincere and conſtant Obedience which Chriſt our Lord will at his coming give unto his faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:60817:58"/>Servants. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.13, &amp;c. <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.28. &amp; 10.36, &amp;c. <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.13. <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.20, &amp;c. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.12.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> You having now ſpoken of God's Work of preparing Believers for Glory, it remains therefore that you ſpeak of that Work of God, which is for the poſſeſſing of Believers with this Glory by Jeſus Chriſt. <hi>What ſay you of it?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> This may more conveniently be ſpoken of in the conſideration of that ſecond thing relating to God's Work of ruling among Men by Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, which I ſaid is his Work of Judging the World by Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb n="112" facs="tcp:60817:59"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IX. </hi>Of God's Work of Government in Judging the World by Jeſus Chriſt.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> WEll then, let us diſcourſe of God's Work in judging the World by Jeſus Chriſt; <hi>What in the general have you learn'd concerning it?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> This I have learned in general, <hi>That God hath appointed a day in the which he will judg the World in Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs by that Man</hi> Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>whom he hath ordained, whereof he hath given aſſurance unto all Men, in that he hath raiſed him from the Dead.</hi> Act. 17.31. Rom. 2.16.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What are we to underſtand by the Day which God hath appointed?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> This Day is that time when Jeſus ſhall come from Heaven in the Glory of his Father, with his Angels. <hi>Acts</hi> 1.11. 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4.16. <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.27. &amp; 25.31, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="113" facs="tcp:60817:59"/>
               <p>Q. <hi>But when ſhall this time be?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> At the end of the World; but <hi>the day and hour,</hi> Jeſus ſaid, <hi>No Man knoweth, no, not the Angels which are in Heaven, neither the Son, but the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther only.</hi> Mat. 24.36. Mark 13.32.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is it for God to judg the World by the Man Jeſus Chriſt, whom he hath ordained?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The meaning is, That God al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he be the Judg of all, yet will not himſelf judg the World, but by Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>to whom he hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted all Judgment,</hi> giving him Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority to execute the ſame, having ordained him to be the Judg of Quick and Dead. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.2, 3. <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.22, &amp;c. <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.16. <hi>Act.</hi> 10.42.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What did Jeſus that God did thus exalt him?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> He was obedient unto Death, even the Death of the Croſs. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.8, 9, &amp;c. <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.9.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Whom will God judg by Jeſus Chriſt?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> God will by Jeſus Chriſt judg
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:60817:60"/>the Angels that ſinned, and all Men, both Quick and Dead, at his Appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Kingdom. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.4. <hi>Jud.</hi> 6. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.3. <hi>Jam.</hi> 2.19. <hi>Act.</hi> 10.42. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.5. <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.10. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.10. <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.15. &amp; 11.22.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What are we to underſtand by the Quick and Dead?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> We are to underſtand by the Quick, or Living, all Men that ſhall be found alive at the coming of Chriſt; and by the Dead, all both good and bad, that died before his coming.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>But how ſhall theſe be brought un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Judgment?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Thus: all the Dead, both the Juſt and Unjuſt, ſhall be raiſed, and then all Men ſhall by the Angels be gathered and brought before Chriſt, ſitting on the Throne of his Glory. <hi>Acts</hi> 24.15. <hi>John</hi> 5.28, 29. <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.31, 32.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Is there any thing in ſpecial to be obſerved here concerning the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="115" facs="tcp:60817:60"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Yes; for we are taught, That the Dead in Chriſt ſhall riſe firſt; and that they, together with thoſe Believers that ſhall be alive at the coming of Chriſt, ſhall be caught up in the Clouds, to meet the Lord in the Air.</p>
               <p>[1 Theſſ. 4.13, &amp;c. <hi>But I would not have you to be ignorant, Brethren, concerning them which are aſleep,</hi> [that is, the Faithful which are Dead] <hi>that ye ſorrow not even as others which have no Hope. For if we believe that Jeſus died, and roſe again, even ſo them alſo which ſleep in Jeſus, will God bring with him. For this we ſay unto you by the Word of the Lord, That we</hi> [Believers] <hi>which are alive, and remain unto the coming of the Lord, ſhall not prevent</hi> [that is, ſhall not come be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore] <hi>them which are aſleep. For the Lord himſelf ſhall deſcend from Heaven with a ſhout, with the Voice of the Arch-Angel, and with the Trump of God: and the dead in Chriſt ſhall riſe firſt. Then we which are alive, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main, ſhall be caught up together with them in the Clouds, to meet the Lord in the Air: and ſo ſhall we ever be with the Lord.</hi> See alſo 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.22, 23, 52.]</p>
               <pb n="116" facs="tcp:60817:61"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Now tell me, <hi>What is it for God to judg the World in Righteouſneſs by Jeſus Christ?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> God by Jeſus Chriſt will judg the World in Righteouſneſs, that is, Righteouſly, by rewarding every Man according to his Practice or Works, whether Good or Evil: for this Judgment is a Juſt or Righteous Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. <hi>Matth.</hi> 16.27. <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.6. <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.23. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.8. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.10. &amp; 11.15. <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.12, 13. &amp; 22.12. <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.5. <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.30.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>But what is it for God by Jeſus Chriſt to judg every Man according to his Works?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Here are two things to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the first?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The firſt is; That God by Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt will judg every Man: for all muſt ſtand before the Judgment Seat of Chriſt, and give an account of themſelves unto God. <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.10, 11, 12. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.1. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.9. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.10. <hi>Jam.</hi> 2.12.</p>
               <pb n="117" facs="tcp:60817:61"/>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the Second?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Second is; That God by Jeſus Chriſt will judg every Man ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his Works; that is, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out reſpect of Perſons, and according to Truth and Right. <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.11. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.17. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 19.7. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.9. <hi>Col.</hi> 3.23. <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.2. <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.2. <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.4. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 96.13. <hi>Gen.</hi> 18.25. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 9.4. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 10.2. <hi>Job</hi> 34.23. 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1.5, 6. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.8. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 45.6. <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.8.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Can you explain this in a ſpecial Application to Men, whom God will juſtify and condemn by Jeſus Chriſt at the last Day?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> I can.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How do you ſet it forth in refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to thoſe whom God by Jeſus Christ will juſtify at the laſt Day?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Thus it may be done: God will render to every Man Eternal Life; who according to the Truth mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted to him, does, <hi>by patient conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance in well-doing, ſeek for Glory, and Honour, and Immortality;</hi> and that God will make them to exceed
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:60817:62"/>thoſe in Glory, whom they exceed in Righteouſneſs. <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.6, 7, 10. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.41. <hi>Matth.</hi> 20.23. <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.3. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.8. <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.17.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How do you ſet it forth in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to them whom God by Jeſus Chriſt will condemn at the laſt Day?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> God will render Indignation and Wrath unto every one that is Contentious, and does not obey the Truth, as manifeſted either without the Law, or under the Law, or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Goſpel; and that God will render the greateſt Puniſhment to the greateſt Offenders. <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.8, 9, 12, &amp;c. 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1.8, 9. <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.22, 24. <hi>Luk.</hi> 12.47, 48. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.20, 21. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.6. <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.14.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> When you ſay, That God by Jeſus Chriſt will render to Men this or that; <hi>What mean you by that word?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> I mean not only that God by Jeſus Chriſt will judg them, to ſuch or ſuch a Condition, but will alſo bring them into it. <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.31, to the end of the Chapter.</p>
               <pb n="119" facs="tcp:60817:62"/>
               <p>Q. <hi>What will follow this Judgment?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Firſt after this Judgment, all the Enemies of Chriſt being put un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his Feet, and all things ſubdued unto him, <hi>the Son ſhall deliver up the Kingdom to God, even the Father, and ſhall himſelf alſo be ſubject to him that put all things under him, that God may be all in all.</hi> 1 Cor. 15.24, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What elſe will follow?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> In reſpect of the Righteous this will follow: They being adjudged by Chriſt <hi>to inherit the Kingdom pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for them from the Foundation of the World;</hi> and having their vile Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy changed, that it may be faſhioned like unto Chriſt's glorious Body, ſhall enter into the Joy of their Lord, where they ſhall live, reſt, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joice, with fulneſs of joy for ever and ever. <hi>Matth.</hi> 25.34. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.21. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.50. <hi>Matth.</hi> 25.21, 23. <hi>Luk.</hi> 20.35, 36. <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.51. 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1.7. <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.9. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.6. &amp; 4.13. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16.11.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>But what ſhall follow in reſpect of the Wicked?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="120" facs="tcp:60817:63"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Wicked being judged to depart from Chriſt into everlaſting Fire, prepared for the Devil and his Angels, ſhall be caſt Body and Soul into Hell <hi>[Geenna]</hi> that Furnace of Fire, where ſhall be wailing and gnaſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Teeth. <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.41. &amp; 10.28. &amp; 13.42.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What from the conſideration here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of may Sinners now be exhorted and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded to?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> They may hence be exhorted and perſwaded to <hi>repent and be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted, that their Sins may be blotted out, when the times of refreſhing come from the preſence of the Lord.</hi> Act. 3.19. &amp; 17.30, 31.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What from the conſideration of the aforeſaid Judgment, and that which follows, may Converts, or Believers, be exhorted and perſwaded to?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> They may hence be exhorted and perſwaded to be <hi>ſtedfaſt, unmove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, always abounding in the Work of the Lord.</hi> 1 Cor. 15.58.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <pb n="121" facs="tcp:60817:63"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. X. </hi>Some particular Duties which Believers ought to know and perform.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> HAving now a fit occaſion, we may here, as in a place moſt convenient, diſcourſe of Good Works, or particular Duties, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in Believers ought to be exerciſed; but ſeeing we have already mentioned many of them which come under the conſideration of Godlineſs, I ſhall deſire to hear from you ſomething of what you have learned, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly concerning Righteouſneſs and So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>briety, of which hitherto you have been almoſt ſilent. Now obſerve and anſwer my Queſtions, of which the firſt ſhall be this:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>What is the Duty of Believers to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Men as Men?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> This in the general is expreſt by our Saviour thus: <hi>All things what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever ye would that Men ſhould do to
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:60817:64"/>you; do ye even ſo to them: for this is the Law and the Prophets.</hi> Mat. 7.12.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How can you expreſs the ſame more particularly?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Thus: To render to all their Dues whatſoever they may juſtly challenge and require of us as their right; and to do good to all.</p>
               <p>[Rom. 13.7. <hi>Render therefore to all their Dues, Tribute to whom Tribute is due, Cuſtom to whom Cuſtom, Fear to whom Fear, Honour to whom Honour.</hi> Prov. 3.27. <hi>With-hold not good from them to whom it is due,</hi> [Hebr. from the Owners thereof] <hi>when it is in the power of thine hand to do it.</hi> Gal. 6.10. <hi>As we have opportunity, let us do good unto all Men, eſpecially to them that are of the Houſhold of Faith.</hi> 1 Theſſ. 5.15. <hi>See that none ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Evil for Evil unto any Man; but ever fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low that which is good, both among your ſelves, and to all Men.</hi> Rom. 16.19. <hi>I would have you wiſe unto that which is Good, and ſimple unto that which is Evil.</hi> 1 Pet. 3.13.]</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>But what is it to render to every one his due.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To render to others their Due, is, To ſpeak truly, <hi>(a)</hi> and deal juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:60817:64"/>with them <hi>(b):</hi> and therefore not to abuſe and wrong them by ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>(c),</hi> flattery <hi>(d)</hi> and evil ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>(e),</hi> as they do that are Revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers <hi>(f),</hi> Scoffers <hi>(g),</hi> Whiſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers <hi>(h),</hi> Backbiters <hi>(i),</hi> Slande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers <hi>(k),</hi> Falſe-Accuſers <hi>(l),</hi> Falſe Witneſs-bearers <hi>(m),</hi> unjuſt Judges, <hi>(n)</hi> and the like, and not to be any wayes injurious to them in their Life <hi>(o),</hi> Liberty <hi>(p),</hi> Eſtates <hi>(q),</hi> Relations <hi>(r),</hi> and the like; nor hurtful to them, as to their everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Concerns, by corrupting them in their Souls and Lives <hi>(ſ),</hi> or hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering them from or in that Faith and Love which is in Chriſt Jeſus <hi>(t).</hi>
               </p>
               <p>[<hi>(a)</hi> John 4.18. Prov. 12.17. Zech. 8.16. Epheſ. 4.25. <hi>(b)</hi> Iſa. 26.10. Mich. 6.8. 2 King. 12.15. 1 Theſſ. 2.10. Iſa. 33.15. Pſal. 15.2. Tit. 2.11. <hi>(c)</hi> Lev. 19.11. Col. 3.9. Joh. 8.44. Rev. 21.27. 1 Tim. 4.2. <hi>(d)</hi> Pſal. 12.2, 3. 1 Theſſ. 2.5. <hi>(e)</hi> Tit. 3.2. <hi>(f)</hi> 1 Cor. 6.10. 1 Pet. 2.23. <hi>(g)</hi> 2 Pet. 3.3. <hi>(h)</hi> Rom. 1.29. Prov. 16.28. 2 Cor. 12.20. <hi>(i)</hi> Rom. 1.30. <hi>(k)</hi> 1 Tim. 3.11. Prov. 10.18. Pſal. 101.5. Jer. 9.4.
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:60817:65"/>
                  <hi>(l)</hi> 2 Tim. 3.3. <hi>(m)</hi> Exod. 20.16. Mat. 15.19. <hi>(n)</hi> Luk. 18.6. Pſalm. 82.6. <hi>(o)</hi> Exod. 20.13. <hi>(p)</hi> Jer. 34.15. Heb. 11.36. <hi>(q)</hi> Exod. 20.15. Epheſ. 4.28. <hi>(r)</hi> Exod. 20.14. <hi>(ſ)</hi> Mat. 23.15. 2 Pet. 2. Chapt. <hi>(t)</hi> Mat. 23.13. Act. 13.8.]</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>And what is it to do good to all?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To do good to all, is in imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of God, to be merciful and kind to them, in reſpect both of their Bouls and Bodies. [<hi>Pſal.</hi> 37.26. <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.7. <hi>Luk.</hi> 6.36. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.4. <hi>Luk.</hi> 6.35. <hi>Col.</hi> 3.12.]</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>But what if they be Enemies to them, and perſecute them?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Although they be ſo, yet muſt Believers be merciful and kind unto them.</p>
               <p>[Mat. 5.44, &amp;c. <hi>I ſay unto you, Love your Enemies; Bleſs them that curſe you; Do good to them that hate you; and pray for them that deſpitefully uſe you, and perſecute you,</hi> &amp;c]</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What then, muſt Believers be a peaceable People?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="125" facs="tcp:60817:65"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Yes; They muſt follow Peace with all Men. And if it be poſſible, as much as in them lieth, live peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably [or be at peace] with all Men. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.14. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.18.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>But how ſhould Believers endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to be at peace with all Men?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> They ſhould endeavour it, by not provoking others to Anger <hi>(a),</hi> in doing them wrong <hi>(b),</hi> or in pleaſing themſelves, in that which is diſpleaſing to others, and wherein they may deny themſelves for their Neighbours good <hi>(c);</hi> alſo by not being eaſily provoked by others <hi>(d),</hi> as when they ſuffer, without any Contention, ſuch Offences that may be eaſily born <hi>(e);</hi> alſo by abſtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from all Revenge <hi>(f),</hi> and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing appeaſable <hi>(g),</hi> and ready to forgive, when they meet with grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Injuries <hi>(h).</hi> Laſtly, By being courteous to all <hi>(i),</hi> and forward to do good to all, in that which they will acknowledg for good <hi>(k),</hi> as by giving and lending to them <hi>(l),</hi>
                  <pb n="126" facs="tcp:60817:66"/>or being ready in any thing to help and aſſiſt them in their need <hi>(m).</hi>
               </p>
               <p>[<hi>(a)</hi> Gal. 5.26. <hi>(b)</hi> 1 Sam. 1.6, 7. <hi>(c)</hi> Rom. 15.1, 2, 3. <hi>(d)</hi> 1 Cor. 13.5. <hi>(e)</hi> Mat. 5.38, 39, <hi>&amp;c. (f)</hi> Rom. 1.31. <hi>(g)</hi> Chap. 12.17, 19. Matth. 6.12, 14, 15. Mat. 18.21, <hi>&amp;c. (h)</hi> Luk. 17.3, 4. Matth. 23.34. <hi>(i)</hi> 1 Pet. 3.8. <hi>(k)</hi> 1 Pet. 3.13. <hi>(l)</hi> Mat. 5.42. <hi>(m)</hi> Tit. 3.1, 2. <hi>Put them in mind to be ſubject to Principalities and Powers, to obey Magiſtrates, to be ready to every good Work, to ſpeak evil of no Man,</hi> [<hi>Gr.</hi> to blaſpheme no Man]; <hi>to be no Brawlers, but gentle, ſhewing all meekneſs unto all Men.</hi> Jam. 3.17. <hi>The Wiſdom that is from Above, is firſt pure, then peaceable, gentle and eaſy to be intreated, full of Mercy and good Fruits, without partiality,</hi> [or without wrangling] <hi>and without hypocriſy.</hi> See <hi>Job</hi> 29.12, &amp;c.]</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> I would hear ſomething which you have learn'd concerning the Duty of Believers in their ſeveral Relations to others: and firſt, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the ſame Kingdom or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Wealth; Here tell me, <hi>What is their Duty who govern, as in a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom the King doth, and they that are
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:60817:66"/>ſent of him for the puniſhment of Evil Doers, and for the praiſe of them that do well?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> He that ruleth over Men, muſt be juſt, ruling in the Fear of God. 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 23.3.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is their Duty toward their Governors?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> They muſt <hi>ſubmit themſelves to every Ordinance of Man</hi> [<hi>Gr.</hi> to every Humane Creature, (that is) to every one whom Men ſet up to Rule and Govern] <hi>for the Lord's ſake,</hi> [that is, for Conſcience-ſake] <hi>whether it be to the King as Supream, or unto Governors, as unto them that are ſent by him, for the puniſhment of Evil-doers, and for the praiſe of them that do well.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>[1 Pet. 2.13, 14. See the thirteenth Chapter of the Epiſtle to the <hi>Romans.</hi> See <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.1.]</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>VVhat is their Duty, being Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands, toward their VVives?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> An Huſband ought to love his Wife as himſelf, nouriſhing and che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:60817:67"/>Her as his own Body, ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering her due Benevolence, and giving honour to the Wife, as to the weaker Veſſel, and not being bitter unto her, and all this, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding ſhe be an Unbeliever, whom therefore he muſt not forſake, but muſt endeavour her Converſion. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.25, &amp;c. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.3, &amp;c. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.7. <hi>Col.</hi> 3.19. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.11, 16.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the Duty of Wives to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward their Husbands?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A Wife ought to love her Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, and to ſubmit to him as to the Lord, by reverencing and obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him, and muſt render unto him due Benevolence, and all this, though he be an Unbeliever. [<hi>Tit.</hi> 2.4. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.22, 23, 24, 33. <hi>Col.</hi> 3.18. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.1, &amp;c. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.3, &amp;c. <hi>verſ.</hi> 10, &amp;c.]</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the Duty of Parents to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward their Children?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is the Duty of Parents not to provoke their Children to Wrath, leſt they be diſcouraged, but to bring
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:60817:67"/>them up in the Nurture and Admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition of the Lord, and to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide for them. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.4. <hi>Col.</hi> 3.21. <hi>Prov.</hi> 29.15. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.15. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.8.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the Duty of Children to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards their Parents?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is the Duty of Children to honour their Father and Mother. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.2. <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.12. <hi>Mal.</hi> 1.6.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>But what is it for Children to honour their Father and Mother?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Firſt, Children that are under the Power of their Parents, ought to honour them, by obeying them in the Lord.</p>
               <p>[Epheſ. 6.1, 2, 3. <hi>Children obey your Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents in the Lord, for this is right. Honour thy Father and thy Mother, (which is the firſt Commandment with promiſe) that it may be well with thee, and that thou mayeſt live long on the Earth.</hi> Col. 3.20. <hi>Children, obey your Parents in all things,</hi> (which they as Parents may command) <hi>for this is well-pleaſing unto the Lord.</hi> See <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.30. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.2.]</p>
               <p>Secondly, Children under the
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:60817:68"/>Power of their Parents, ought to honour them, by ſo regarding them when they juſtly correct, as to be aſhamed, and amend, and not to be provoked to Anger when ſo chaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.9.</p>
               <p>[Thus it is written in the Law of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes;</hi> Deut. 21.18, <hi>&amp;c. If a Man have a ſtubborn and rebellious Son, which will not obey the Voice of his Father, or the Voice of his Mother, and that when they have cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtened him, will not hearken unto them; then ſhall his Father and his Mother lay hold on him, and bring him out unto the Elders of his City, and unto the Gate of his Place; and they ſhall ſay unto the Elders of his City, This our Son is ſtubborn and rebellious, he will not obey our Voice, he is a Glutton and a Drunkard. And all the Men of his City ſhall ſtone him with Stones that he die: So ſhalt thou put Evil away from among you, and all</hi> Iſrael <hi>ſhall hear and fear.</hi>]</p>
               <p>Thirdly, Children under or not under the Power of their Parents, ought to honour them, by reverencing their Father and Mother.</p>
               <p>[Levit. 19.3. <hi>Ye ſhall fear</hi> [reverence] <hi>every Man his Mother and his Father.</hi> Deut.
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:60817:68"/>27.16. <hi>Curſed be he that ſetteth light by his Father or his Mother, and all the People ſhall ſay,</hi> Amen. Prov. 30.17. <hi>The Eye that mocketh at his Father, and deſpiſeth to obey his Mother, the Ravens of the Valey ſhall pick it out, and the young Eagles ſhall eat it.</hi>]</p>
               <p>Fourthly, All Children ought to honour their Parents, by ſhewing the natural Affection of Children to them, in being a delight and glory to them, and uſeful and profitable to them in what they can.</p>
               <p>[Prov. 10.1. <hi>A wiſe Son maketh a glad Father, but a fooliſh Son is the heavineſs of his Mother.</hi> Prov. 23.24. <hi>The Father of the Righteous ſhall greatly rejoice, and he that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getteth a wiſe Child, ſhall have joy of him.</hi> Prov. 28.7. <hi>Whoſo keepeth the Law, is a wiſe Son, but he that is a Companion of riotous Men, ſhameth his Father.</hi> Matth. 15.4, <hi>&amp;c. God commanded, ſaying, Honour thy Father and Mother; and he that curſeth Father or Mother, let him die the Death. But ye</hi> [Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees] <hi>ſay, Whoſoever ſhall ſay to his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther or Mother, It is a Gift, by whatſoever thou mighteſt be profited by me, and honour not his Father or Mother, he ſhall be free. Thus</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>have ye made the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment of God of none effect by your Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition.</hi>
                  <pb n="130" facs="tcp:60817:69"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="131" facs="tcp:60817:69"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="132" facs="tcp:60817:70"/>Prov. 19.26. <hi>He that waſteth his Father, and chaſeth away his Mother, is a Son that cauſeth ſhame, and bringeth reproach.</hi> Exod. 21.15. <hi>He that ſmiteth his Father or his Mother, ſhall be ſurely put to death.</hi>]</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the Duty of Maſters to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards their Servants?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 'Tis the Duty of Maſters to give unto their Servants that which is juſt and equal, moderating Threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings. Knowing that their Maſter alſo is in Heaven, and that there is no reſpect of Perſons with him. <hi>Col.</hi> 4.1. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.9.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the Duty of Servants to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward their Maſters?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 'Tis the Duty of Servants, <hi>to count their Maſters worthy of all Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour</hi> [due to Maſters], <hi>and to be obedient to them with fear and trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling,</hi> [that is, pleaſing them well in all things, <hi>not anſwering again,</hi> or gain-ſaying] <hi>in ſingleneſs of their Heart, as unto Christ:</hi> that is, <hi>not with Eye-Service, as Men-pleaſers, but as the Servants of Christ, doing the
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:60817:70"/>VVill of God from the Heart; with good VVill doing ſervice as to the Lord, and not to Men: not purloining, but ſhewing all good fidelity.</hi> And all this <hi>not only to the good and gentle, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to the froward: for this is thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy, if a Man for Conſcience to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward God endure grief, ſuffering wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully.</hi> But if they have Believing Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, they muſt not deſpiſe them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are Brethren, but rather do them Service becauſe they are faithful and beloved, partakers of the Benefit. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.5, &amp;c. <hi>Col.</hi> 3.22, &amp;c. <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.9, &amp;c. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.18, &amp;c. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.1, 2.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the Duty of Believers to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Believers?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Believers ought to love one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with a pure heart fervently, and to continue therein. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.22. <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.1.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>But how are they to ſhew their love one to another?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Firſt, They are to follow after the things that make for Peace, as low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs or humbleneſs, meekneſs, long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuffering,
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:60817:71"/>and the like. <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.19. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.2, 3.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What elſe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> They alſo are to follow after the things wherewith they may edify one another, as by reſtoring them that are taken in a Fault; by confirming, exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, and comforting one another. <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.19. <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.1. 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5.14. <hi>Act.</hi> 15.32. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.24, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Is there any thing elſe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Yes; for Believers ought in an eſpecial manner to be ready unto eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry good Work towards their Brethren, and that with the hazard of their own Lives (if need be) for the relief, ſuccour, and ſafety of their Brethren, when they are poor, ſick, impriſoned, baniſhed, or any otherwiſe in affliction and danger.</p>
               <p>[Gal. 6.10. Heb. 13.16. 1 Joh. 3.16. Joh. 13.34. Mat. 25.34, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Heb. 13.1, 2, 3. 1 Joh. 3.15, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Rom. 12.13. Phil. 2.30.]</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Have you any thing more to add?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> I ſhall ſum up all in this, That Believers ought to rejoice with them that rejoice, and to weep with them
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:60817:71"/>that weep, to be of the ſame mind one towards another, and to ſerve one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in love. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.15, 16. <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.13.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the Duty of their Elders that Teach and Rule among them?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> They ought to feed the Flock of God, <hi>taking the overſight thereof, not by conſtraint, but willingly; not for filthy lucre, but of a ready mind; neither as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Lords over God's Heritage, but being Enſamples to the Flock.</hi> 1 Pet. 5.2, 3.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the Duty of the Flock to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards thoſe that feed them?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Their Duty is, to know, obey and eſteem them very highly in love for their Works ſake, and to communicate to them in all good things. 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5.12, 13. <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.17. <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.6.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> I am now willing to hear what you have learn'd touching the Duty of Believers, in reference to their tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Life, and the good things belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereto, as Pleaſures, Riches, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, and in reference to the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; wherefore I ask you, <hi>What is the Duty of Believers in reference to their Temporal Life?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="136" facs="tcp:60817:72" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Their Duty in the general is, To love their Lives in ſeeking to ſave them, when they may ſo do, and not loſe them for ever; alſo to hate their Lives in not ſeeking to ſave them, when by loſing them they may ſave them for ever. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.10. <hi>Luk.</hi> 14.26.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>When may a Man be ſaid to loſe his Life for ever, in ſeeking to ſave it for a time?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Then when a Man cannot ſave his Life and ſerve God together.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Well; <hi>What is the Duty of Believers for the ſaving of their temporal Lives?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> They as Men truſting in God and obeying him, muſt ſeek to provide that which may preſerve their Lives, and to avoid that which may deſtroy them.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How may they thus ſeek that which may preſerve their Lives?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> When with Prayer and thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs to God daily for their daily Bread, they ſeek to get by diligence in ſome honeſt Imploiment, or, if need be, by Benefits from others, that which is needful, and to keep neceſſary things,
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:60817:72"/>not waſtfully ſpending them, nor ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully with-holding them, when called to lend them unto the Lord.</p>
               <p>[<hi>Mat.</hi> 6.11. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.4, 5. <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.25, &amp;c. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.28. 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4.11, 12. 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 3.6, &amp;c. <hi>Prov.</hi> 6.6, &amp;c. <hi>Luk.</hi> 22.35. <hi>Act.</hi> 4.34. &amp; 20.35. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 3.6. <hi>Prov.</hi> 21.20. &amp; 23.21. &amp; 29.3. &amp; 22.16. <hi>Prov.</hi> 11.24. &amp; 28.27. &amp; 19.17.]</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How must they ſeek to avoid that which may deſtroy their Lives?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Among other things, they muſt firſt keep themſelves free from all ſins, for which God ſometimes doth, or Men juſtly may take away their Lives. <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 55.23. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.30. <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.4. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.15. Secondly, They muſt ſeek to keep themſelves ſafe from thoſe that ſeek their Lives, and this either by Power, when Right and Law arms them againſt their Enemies, or only by Prudence, when Power is want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or may not be uſed lawfully. <hi>Eſth.</hi> 8.11, &amp;c. 1 <hi>King.</hi> 1.12. <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.16, &amp;c. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.15, 16. <hi>Col.</hi> 4.5.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>When muſt Believers hate their Lives in not ſeeking to ſave them?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Then muſt they hate their Lives,
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:60817:73" rendition="simple:additions"/>when they cannot with the perſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their Lives, keep a good Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience towards God. They muſt be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways free to hazard their Lives in the performance of their Duty to God. <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.11. <hi>Matth.</hi> 16.24, &amp;c. <hi>Luk.</hi> 14.26, &amp;c. <hi>Joh.</hi> 12.25. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.17. <hi>Act.</hi> 15.26. &amp; 20.24. <hi>Judg.</hi> 5.18.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Now let us ſpeak concerning Worldly Pleaſures, and their Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: <hi>What have you learn'd touching the Duty of Believers, in reference to worldly Pleaſures?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> I have learn'd, That Believers, who may uſe lawful Pleaſures, muſt be moderate in the uſe of them, and avoid all ſinful Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures and Delights; being chaſt and tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate in ſhunning Adultery, Fornication, Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural Uncleanneſs, Laſciviouſneſs, Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feiting, Gluttony, Drunkenneſs, Rioting or Revelling, Idleneſs, and the like.</p>
               <p>[Eccleſ. 3.12. &amp; 5.18, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> &amp; 9.7, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Phil. 4 5. 1 Cor. 7.29, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Prov. 21.17. Luk 8.14. 1 Tim. 5.6. 2 Tim. 3.4, 11. Heb. 11.25. Tit. 2.12. 1 Pet. 3.2. 1 Theſſ. 4.11. Gal. 5.23. 2 Pet. 1.6. 1 Cor. 9.25, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Tit. 1.8. &amp; 2.2. Gal. 5.19. Epheſ. 5.3. Rom. 1.24, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Deut. 23.17. 1 Cor. 6.9. 1 Tim. 1.10. Jude 7. Exod. 12.19. Levit. 18.23. Mark 7.22. 1 Pet. 4.3. Luke 21.24. Prov. 23.21. Mat. 11.19 Rom. 13.13. Gal. 5.21. Ezek. 10.49. 1 Tim. 5 13. 2 Theſſ. 3.11.]</p>
               <pb n="139" facs="tcp:60817:73" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the Duty of Believers that are in ſorrow by reaſon of Afflictions?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is their Duty to be patient in all, to rejoice in the Lord always, and to endeavour that all may be for profit and good unto them. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.12. <hi>Jam.</hi> 5.7, &amp;c. <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.4. <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.2. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.11.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Let us now ſpeak of Worldly Riches; <hi>What is the Duty of Believers that are Rich?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Their Hearts muſt not be lifted up [in Pride] becauſe of their Riches. They muſt not deſpiſe the Poor, nor oppreſs them, nor truſt in uncertain Riches, but in the living God; and they ought to be rich in good Works. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 28.5. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 49.6. <hi>Prov.</hi> 28.11. <hi>Jam.</hi> 2.6. <hi>Prov.</hi> 17.5. &amp; 14.31. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.17.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is their Duty who are not Rich?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> They muſt be content with the things that they have, not willing, reſolving and labouring to be rich, nor envying thoſe that are. <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.5. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.8, &amp;c. <hi>Prov.</hi> 23.4. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.4. <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.13. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73.2, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> We are now to ſpeak of Worldly Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour: <hi>Tell me, how muſt they that are in Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour behave themſelves?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> They muſt be lowly, and walk wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of the Honour they have. <hi>Prov.</hi> 11.2. &amp; 16.18, 19. <hi>Act.</hi> 24.2.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Upon this occaſion, tell me, <hi>What is
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:60817:74" rendition="simple:additions"/>the way of getting and keeping an honourable Eſteem and Reputation with others?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The right way to get and keep our ſelves in an honourable Eſteem with others; is, To abſtain from all appearance of Evil; to excel in Wiſdom and Vertue, and to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>have our ſelves modeſtly and diſcreetly in all Converſe with others.</p>
               <p>[1 Theſſ. 5.22. 1 Cor. 14.12. 1 King 4.30 Phil. 2.29, 30. Prov. 31.10, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> &amp; 15.33. Luke 14.8, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 1 Tim. 2.9, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 1 Cor. 11.13, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Pſal. 112.5. Tit. 2 5. Prov. 11.22. &amp; 12.16. &amp; 19.11. &amp; 18.13. Eccleſ. 10 1. Prov. 25.9, 10.]</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> You have now ſpoken much of good Works, <hi>Have you any thing more to ſay of this Matter?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> There is much more to be ſpoken con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning good Works; but I am willing to conclude this Diſcourſe now with that of the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> in <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.8. <hi>Finally, Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, whatſoever things are true, whatſoever things are juſt, whatſoever things are pure, whatſoever things are lovely, whatſoever things are of good report; if there be any Vertue, and if there be any Praiſe, think on theſe things.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:60817:74"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
